<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The security of English-mens lives, or, The trust, power, and duty of the grand jurys of England explaining according to the fundamentals of the English government, and the declarations of the same made in Parliament by many statutes / published for the prevention of popish designs against the lives of many Protestant lords and commoners who stand firm to the religion and ancient government of England.</title>
            <author>Somers, John Somers, Baron, 1651-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60883</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4643</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33648</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13544962</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13544962</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100111</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60883)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100111)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1558:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The security of English-mens lives, or, The trust, power, and duty of the grand jurys of England explaining according to the fundamentals of the English government, and the declarations of the same made in Parliament by many statutes / published for the prevention of popish designs against the lives of many Protestant lords and commoners who stand firm to the religion and ancient government of England.</title>
                  <author>Somers, John Somers, Baron, 1651-1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>168 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. Mitchel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints to Somers.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Dublin University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Grand jury --  England.</term>
               <term>Justice, Administration of --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100111:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SECURITY OF Engliſh-Mens Lives, OR THE TRUST, POWER, and DUTY OF THE <hi>Grand Iurys</hi> OF ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>Explained according to the Fundamentals of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, and the Declarations of the ſame made in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament by many Statutes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed for the Prevention of Popiſh Deſigns againſt the Lives of many Proteſtant Lords and Commoners, who ſtand firm to the Religion and ancient Government of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed for</hi> T. Mitchel. 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:100111:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100111:2"/>
            <p>THE Principal Ends of all Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Government, and of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Society, were the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of Mens Lives, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Properties, mutual Aſſiſtance, and Help, each unto other, and Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for their common Benefit and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; and wherethe Fundamental Laws and Conſtitution of any Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have been wiſely adapted unto thoſe Ends, ſuch Countries ane King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms have increaſed in Virtue, Prow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs, Wealth and Happineſs, whil'ſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers through the want of ſuch excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Conſtitutions, or neglect of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving them, have been a Prey to the Pride, Luſt and Cruelty of the moſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and the People have had no Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Eſtates, Liberties or Lives, but from their Grace and Pleaſure: They have been many times forced to welter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in each others Blood in their Maſters
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100111:3"/>quarrel for Dominion, and at beſt they <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erved like Beaſts of Burden, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ntinual, baſe ſubſerviency to their <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ers Vices, have loſt all ſenſe of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Religion, Virtue and Manhood.</p>
            <p>Our Anceſtors have been famous in <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir Generations for Wiſdom, Piety, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>d courage, in forming and preſerving <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Body of Laws to ſecure themſelves and their Poſterities from Slavery and Oppreſſion, and to maintain their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Freedoms; to be ſubject only to the Laws made by their own Conſent in their general Aſſemblies, and to be put in Execution chiefly by themſelves, their Officers and Aſſiſtants, to be guarded and defended from all Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and Force, by their own Arms, kept in their own hands, and uſed at their own charge under their Princes Conduct; entruſting nevertheleſs an ample Power to their Kings, and other Magiſtrates, that they may may do all the Good, and enjoy all the Happineſs that the largeſt Soul of man can ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly wiſh; and carefully providing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100111:3"/>ſuch means of correcting and puniſhing their Miniſters and Councillors, if they tranſgreſſed the Laws, that they might not dare to abuſe or oppreſs the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or deſign againſt their Freedom or Welfare.</p>
            <p>This Body of Laws our Anceſtors always eſteemed the beſt Inheritance they could leave to their Poſterities, well knowing that theſe were the ſacred Fence of their Lives, Liberties, and Eſtates, and an unqueſtionable Title whereby they might call what they had their own, or ſay they were their own Men: The ineſtimable value of this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance moved our Progenitors with great reſolution bravely from Age to Age to defend it; and it now falls to our Lot to preſerve it againſt the Dark Contrivances of a Popiſh Faction, who would by Frauds, Sham-Plots, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous Perjuries, deprive us of our Birth-rights, and turn the points of our Swords (our Laws) into our own Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els; they have impudently ſcandalized our Parliaments, with Deſigns to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100111:4"/>the Monarchy, becauſe they would have excluded a Popiſh Succeſſor, and provided for the Security of the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Lives of all Proteſtants: They have cauſed Lords and Commoners to be for a long time kept in Priſons, and ſuborned Witneſſes to ſwear matters of Treaſon againſt them; endeavouring thereby, not only to cut off ſome who had eminently appeared in Parliament for our antient Laws, but through them to blaſt the Repute of Parliaments themſelves, and to leſſen the Peoples Confidence in thoſe great Bulwarks of their Religion and Government.</p>
            <p>The preſent purpoſe is to ſhew how well our Worthy fore-Fathers have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in our Law for the ſafety of our Lives, not only againſt all attempts of open Violence, by the ſevere puniſhment of Robbers, Murtherers, and the like, but the ſecret poyſonous Arrows that flie in the dark, to deſtroy the Innocent by falſe Accuſation and Perjuries. Our Law-makers foreſaw both their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from the Malice, and Paſſion,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100111:4"/>that might cauſe ſome of private con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, to accuſe others falſly in the Courts of Juſtice, and the great hazards of Worthy and Eminent Mens Lives, from the Malice, Emulation, and Ill De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of corrupt Miniſters of State, or otherwiſe potent, who might commit the moſt odious of Murders in the form and courſe of Juſtice; either by cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting of Judges, as dependant upon them for their Honour and great Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, or by Bribing and Hiring men of depraved Principles, and deſperate Fortunes, to ſwear falſly againſt them; doubtleſs they had heard the Scriptures, and obſerved that the great men of the <hi>Jews</hi> ſought out many to ſwear Treaſon and Blaſphemy againſt Jeſus Chr<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>: They had heard of <hi>Ahab</hi>'s Courtiers and Judges, who, in the Courſe, a<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Form of Juſtice, by falſe Witneſſes, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>thered <hi>Naboth, becauſe he would no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubmit his Properly to an Arbi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rary Power.</hi> Neither were they ignora<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the Antient <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtor<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the peſtilent, falſe Accuſers that aboun<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100111:5"/>in the Reign of ſome of thoſe Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, under whom the greateſt of crimes was to be virtuous: Therefore, as became good Legiſlators, they made as prudent Proviſion as perhaps any Country in the World enjoys, for equal and impartial Adminiſtration of Juſtice in all the concerns of the Peoples Lives; that every man, whether Lord or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner, might be in ſafety, whilſt they lived in due Obedience to the Laws.</p>
            <p>For this purpoſe it is made a Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental in our Government, that (un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſs it be by Parliament,<note place="margin">See Ld <hi>Cookes Inſtit.</hi> 3d part, p. 40.</note> no mans Life ſhall be touched for any crime whatſoever, ſave by the Judgment of at leaſt 24 men; that is, 12 or more,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Mag. Chart. Cooke<hi>'s 2 part of</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. <hi>p. 50, 51.</hi>
               </note> to find the Bill of Indictment, whether he be Peer of the Realm, or Commoner, and 12 Peers, or above, if a Lord, if not 12 Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moners to give the Judgment upon the general Iſſue of not guilty joyned; of theſe 24 the firſt 12 are called the Grand
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100111:5"/>Inqueſt, or the Grand Jury, for the extent of their power, and in regard that their number muſt be more than 12, ſometimes 23, or 25, never were leſs than 13, Twelve whereof at leaſt muſt agree to every Indictment, or elſe 'tis no legal Verdict; If 11 of 21, or of 13, ſhould agree to find a Bill of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment, it were no Verdict. The other Twelve, in Commoners Caſes, are called the Petit-Jury, and their nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mber is ever Twelve; but the Jury for a Peer of the Realm may be more in number, though of like Authority. The Office and Power of theſe Juries is <hi>Judicial,</hi> they only are the Judges from whoſe Sentence the Indicted are to expect Life or Death; upon their Integrity and Underſtanding, the Lives of all that are brought into Judgment do ultimately depend; from their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict there lies no Appeal, by finding Guilty or not Guilty; they do compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cately Reſolve both Law, and Fact.</p>
            <p>As it hath been the Law, ſo it hath allways been the Cuſtom, and Practice
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100111:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100111:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:100111:7"/>of theſe Juries, upon all general Iſſues, pleaded in Caſes Civil as well as Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, to judge both of the Law and Fact.<note place="margin">See the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports</hi> of the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Vaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> p. 150.151.</note> So it is ſaid in the Report of the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Vaughan,</hi> in <hi>Buſhel</hi>'s Caſe, that theſe Juries determine the Law in all matters where Iſſue is joyned and tried, in the Principal Caſe, whether the Iſſue be about a Treſpaſs or a Debt, or Diſſeizin in Aſſizes, or a Tort, or any ſuch like, unleſs they ſhould pleaſe to give a ſpecial Verdict, with an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite faith in the Judgment of the Court, to which none can oblige them againſt their Wills.</p>
            <p>Theſe laſt 12 muſt be Men of equal condition with the Party Indicted, and are called his Peers, therefore if it be a Peer of the Realm, they muſt be all ſuch, when Indicted at the Suit of the King; and in the caſe of Commoners, every Man of the 12 muſt agree to the Verdict, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without compulſion, fear, or menace, elſe it is no Verdict. Whether the caſe of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100111:7"/>a Peer be harder, I will not determine. Our Anceſtors were careful that all men of the like condition, and quality, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to be ſenſible of each others infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, ſhould mutually be Judges each of others lives, and alternately taſt of Subjection and Rule; every man being equally liable to be Accuſed, or Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and perhaps to be ſuddenly judged by the Party, of whom he is at preſent Judge, if he be found innocent. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be Lord or Commoner that is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted, the Law intends (as near as may be) that his equals that Judge him, ſhould be his Companions, known to him, and he to them, or at leaſt his Neighbours or Dwellers near about the place where the Crime is ſuppoſed to have been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, to whom ſomething of the Fact muſt probably be known; and though the Lords are not appointed to be of the Neighbourhood to the Indicted Lord, yet the Law ſuppoſes them to be Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and perſonally well known each unto other, being preſumed to be a ſmall number (as they have anciently been)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100111:8"/>and to have met yearly, or oftner in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as by Law they ought, beſides their other meetings, as the hereditary Councillers of the Kings of <hi>England.</hi> If time hath altered the caſe of the Lords, as to the number, indifferency, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiality of the Peers, it hath been, and may be worthy of the Parliaments con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and the greater duty is incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent upon Grand Juries to examine with the utmoſt diligence the Evidence againſt Peers, before they find a Bill of Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt any of them if in truth it may put their Lives in greater danger.</p>
            <p>It is not deſigned at this time to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake a diſcourſe of Petit-Juries, but to conſider the Nature and Power of Grand Inqueſts, and to ſhew how much the Reputation, the Fortunes, and the Lives of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men depend upon the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious performance of their Duty.</p>
            <p>It was abſolutely neceſſary for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Government, and the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of every Mans life and intereſt, that ſome ſhould be truſted to inquire after all ſuch as by Treaſons, Fellonies, or
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100111:8"/>leſſer Crimes, diſturbed the peace, that they might be proſecuted, and brought to condign puniſhment; and it was no leſs needful for every mans quiet and ſafety, that the truſt of ſuch inquiſitions ſhould be put into the hands of Perſons of underſtanding, and integrity, indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, and impartial, that might ſuffer no man to be falſely accuſed, or defamed, nor the lives of any to be put in jeopar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, by the malicious conſpiracies of great or ſmall, or the Perjuries of any profligate wretches: For theſe neceſſary, honeſt ends was the inſtitution of Grand Juries.</p>
            <p>Our Anceſtors thoughtit not beſt to truſt this great concern of their Lives and Intereſts in the Hands of any Officer of the King's, or in any Judges named by him, nor in any certain number of men during life, leſt they ſhould be awed or influenced by great men, corrupted by bribes, flatteries, or love of power, or become negligent, or partial to Friends and Relations, or purſue their own Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels or private Revenges, or connive at
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100111:9"/>the Conſpiracies of others, and indict thereupon. But this truſt of enquiring out, and Indicting all the Criminals in a County, is placed in men of the ſame County, more at leaſt than Twelve of the moſt honeſt, and moſt ſufficient for Knowledge, and Ability of Mind and Eſtate, to be from time to time at the Seſſions and Aſſizes, and all other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions of Oyer and Terminer, named and returned by the chief Sworn Officer of the County, the Sheriff, (who was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by expreſs Law anciently choſen an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually by the people of every County and truſted with the Execution of all Writ and Proceſſes of the Law, and with the power of the County to ſuppreſs all Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olences, unlawful Routs, Riots, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions. Yet our Laws left not the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of theſe Grand Inqueſts abſolutely to the Will of the Sheriffs, but have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in general their Qualifications, who ſhall Enquire and Indict either Lore or Commoner: They ought, by the old common Law, to be lawful Liedg<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> people, of ripe Age, not over aged or in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100111:9"/>firm, and of good Fame amongſt their Neighbours, free from all reaſonable ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of any deſign for himſelf or others, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Eſtates or Lives of any ſuſpected Criminals, or Quarrel, or Controverſie with any of them: They ought to be indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and impartial, even before they are admitted to be ſworn, and of ſufficient Underſtanding and Eſtate for ſo great a Truſt. The ancient Law-Book, called, <hi>Briton,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Brit.</hi> p. 9, and 10.</note> of great Authority, ſays, The She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs, Bailiffs ought to be ſworn to return ſuch as know beſt how to enquire, and diſcover all breaches of the Peace; and leſt any ſhould intrude themſelves, or be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded by others, they ought to be res turned by the Sheriff, without the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination of any, except the Sheriffs Officers. And agreeable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto was the Statute of 11.<note place="margin">See 11. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>H.</hi> 4 in thnſe words. <hi rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Item,</hi> Becauſe of late Inqueſts were taken at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> of perſons named to the Juſtices, without due Return of the Sheriff, of which perſons ſome were
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100111:10"/>outlawed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſome fled to Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary for Treaſon and Felony, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by whom, as well many Offenders were indicted, as other lawful Liedge people of the King not guilty, by Conſpiracy, Abetment, and falſe Imagination of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> againſt the courſe of the common Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is therefore grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for the Eaſe and Quietneſs of the People, that the ſame Indictment, with all its Dependances, be void, and holden for none for ever; and that from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, no Indictment be made by any ſuch perſons, but by Inqueſt of the Kings Liedge People, in the manner as was uſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> returned by the Sheriffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without any denomination to the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> according to the Law of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and if any Indictment be made hereafter, in any point to the contrary,<note place="margin">See <hi>Cooke In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit.</hi> 3d part, fol. 33.</note> the ſame be alſo void, and holden for none for ever.</hi> See alſo the Statute of <hi>Weſtm</hi> 2d cap. 38. and <hi>Artic<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſuper Cortas,</hi> ch. 9.</p>
            <p>So careful have our Parliaments been
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100111:10"/>that the Power of Grand Inqueſts might be placed in the hands of good and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy men; that if one man of a Grand In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, though they be Twenty Three or more, ſhould not be <hi>Liber &amp; Legalis Homo,</hi> or ſuch as the Law requires, and duly returned without denomination to the Sheriff; all the Indictments found by ſuch a Grand Jury, and the proceedings upon them, are void and null. So it was adjudged in <hi>Scarlet</hi>'s caſe.</p>
            <p>I know too well, that the Wiſdom and Care of our Anceſtors, in this Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Grand Juries, hath not been of late conſidered as it ought; nor the Laws concerning them duly obſerved; nor have the Gentlemen and other men of Eſtates, in the ſeveral Counties, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned how inſenſibly their legal Power and Juriſdiction in their Grand and Petit Juries is decayed, and much of the means to preſerve their own Lives and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, taken out of their hands. 'Tis a wonder that they were not more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened with the attempt of the late Ed. Ch. Juſtice <hi>K.</hi> who would have uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100111:11"/>a Lordly, Dictatorian power over the Grand Jury of <hi>Somerſetſhire,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to ſind a Bill of Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for murther, for which they ſaw no Evidence, and upon their refuſal, he not only threatned the Jury, but aſſumed to himſelf an Arbitrary Power to ſine them.</p>
            <p>Here was a bold Battery made upon the ancient Fence of our Reputations, and Lives: If that Juſtice's Will had paſſed for Law, all the Gentlemen of the Grand Juries muſt have been the baſeſt Vaſſals to the Judges, and have been penally obliged, <hi>Jurare in Verba Magiſtri,</hi> to have ſworn to the Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Dictates of the Judges: But thanks be to God, the late long Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (though filled with Penſioners) could not bear ſuch a bold Invaſion of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberty; but upon the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of one Sir <hi>Hugh Windham,</hi> Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the ſaid Jury, and a Member of that Parliament, the Commons brought the then Chief Juſtcie to their Bar, to acknowledge his fault, whereupon the Proſecution ceaſed.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:100111:11"/>
            <p> The Truſt and Power of Grand Juries, is, and ought to be, accounted amongſt the greateſt, and of moſt concern, next to the Legiſlative. The juſtice of the whole Kingdom, in criminal Caſes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt wholly depending upon their Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Integrity, in the due Execution of their Office; Beſides, the Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of all Commoners, the Honour, Reputation, Eſtates, and Lives of all the Nobility of <hi>England,</hi> are ſo far ſubmitted to their Cenſure, that they may bring them into queſtion for Treaſon, or Felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, at their Diſcretion; Their Verdict muſt be entred upon Record, againſt the greateſt Lords, and proceſs muſt legally go out againſt them thereupon, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon them if they can be taken, or to outlaw them, as the Statutes direct; and if any Peer of the Realm, though inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, ſhould juſtly fear a Conſpiracy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Life, and think fit to withdraw, the direction of the Statutes, in proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Outlawry, being rightly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, he could never reverſe the Outlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as the Law now ſtands, ſave by Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100111:12"/>or Act of Parliament. Hence it appears, that in caſe a Grand Jury ſhould be drawn to Indict a Noble Peer unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, either by means of their own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or partiality, or a blind ſubmiſſion to the Direction or Opinion of Judges: One ſuch failure of a Jury, may occaſion the Ruine of any of the beſt or greateſt Families in <hi>England:</hi> I mention this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Grand Juries Power over all the Nobility, only to ſhew their joint In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and Concern with the Commons of <hi>England</hi> in this ancient Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>The Grand Juries are truſted to be the principal means of preſerving the Peace of the whole Kingdom, by the terrour of executing the penal Laws againſt Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, by their Wiſdom, Diligence, and Faithfulneſs in making due Inquiries after all Breaches of the Peace, and bringing every one to anſwer for his crime, at the peril of his Life, Limb, and Eſtate; that every man, who lives within the Law, may ſleep ſecurely in his own Houſe.</p>
            <p>'Tis committed to their Charge and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100111:12"/>Truſt, to take care of bringing Capital Offenders to pay their Lives to Juſtice, and leſſer Criminals to other puniſhments, according to their ſeveral demerits. The Courts, or Judges, or Commiſſioners of Oyer and Terminer, and of Gaol De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery, are to receive only from the Grand Inqueſt, all Capital matters what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, to be put in Iſſue, tried and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before them by the Petit Juries. The whole Stream of Juſtice, in ſuch caſes, either runs freely, or is ſtopped and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed as the Grand Inqueſts do their Duties, either faithfully and prudently, or neglect or omit them.</p>
            <p>And as one part of their Duty is to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict Offenders, ſo another part is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect the Innocent, in their Reputations, Lives and Intereſts, from falſe Accuſers, and malicious Conſpirators: They are to ſearch out the Truth of ſuch Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as come before them, and to reject the Indictment if it be not ſufficiently proved, and farther, if they have reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſuſpicion of Malice, or wicked De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns againſt any mans Life or Eſtate by
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100111:13"/>ſuch as offer a Bill of Indictment; the Laws of God and of the Kingdom, bind them to uſe all poſſible means to diſcover the Villany; and if it appear to them (whereof they are the legal Judges) to be a Conſpiracy, or malicious Combination againſt the Accuſed, they are bound by the higheſt Obligations upon Men and Chriſtians, not only to reject ſuch a Bill of Indictment, but to Indict forth with all the Conſpirators with their Abettors and Aſſociates.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſs there hath been Pride and Covetouſneſs, Malice and deſire of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge in all Ages, from whence have ſprung falſe Accuſations and Conſpiracies; but no Age before us ever hatched ſuch Villanies, as our Popiſh Faction have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived againſt our Religion, Lives, and Liberties. No Hiſtory aſſords an Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of ſuch Forgeries, Perjuries, Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and Combinations of infamous Wretches, as have been lately diſcovered amongſt them, to defame Loyal, Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Proteſtants, and to ſhed their guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Blood in the Form and Courſe of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100111:13"/>and to make the Kings moſt faithful Subjects appear to be the vileſt Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors unto him. In this our miſerable State, Grand Juries are our only Security, in as much as our Lives cannot be drawn into jeoperdy, by all the malicious craſts of the Devil, unleſs ſuch a number of our honeſt Country Men ſhall be ſatisfied in the truth of the Accuſations. For pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of ſuch Plotters of wickedneſs as now abound, was that Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute made in the 42 of <hi>E.</hi> 3.3.<note place="margin">See the Stat. 42 <hi>E.</hi> 3.3.</note> in theſe words: <hi rend="margQuotes">To eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew the miſchiefs and damage done to divers of the Commons by <hi>Falſe Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers,</hi> which oftentimes have made the Accuſations more for Revenge and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Benefit, than for the profit of the King, or of his People; which accuſed perſons, ſome have been taken, and ſometimes cauſed to come before the King's Council by Writ, and otherwiſe, upon grievous pain, againſt the Law; It is aſſented and accorded for the good Government of the Commons, That no man be put to anſwer without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100111:14"/>before Juſtices, or matter of Record, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> according to the old Law of the Land, and if any thing be done to the contrary, it ſhall be void in Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> And (ſaith the Statute of the 25 of <hi>E.</hi> 3.4.) <hi rend="margQuotes">None ſhall be taken by Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, or Suggeſtion made to the King or to his Council, unleſs it be by <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment,</hi> or <hi>Preſentment</hi> of good and lawful People, of the ſame <hi>Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> where ſuch deeds be done, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> That is to ſay, by a Grand Jury.</p>
            <p>All our Lives are thus by Law truſted to the Care of our Grand Inqueſts, that none may be put to anſwer for their lives, unleſs they Indict them. If a cauſleſs Indictment of any man ſhould careleſly paſs from them, his guiltleſs Blood, or what Prejudice ſoever the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed ſhould thereby ſuffer muſt reſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, who by breach of their Truſt were the occaſions of it; their fault can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be excuſed by the proſecution of an Attorney, or Solicitor General, or any other Accuſer, if it were in their power to be more truly informed in the Caſe.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100111:14"/>Whoſoever prevents not an Evil when he may, conſents to it.</p>
            <p>Now to oblige theſe Juries to the more conſcientious care, to Indict all that ſhall appear to them Criminals, and to ſave every Innocent, if it may be, from unjuſt Vexation, and danger, by Malice and Conſpiracy, our Anceſtors appointed an Oath to be impoſed upon them, which cannot be altered, except by Act of Parliament: Therefore every Grand Jury Man is ſworn, as the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, in the words following, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſhall diligently enquire, and true Preſentment make of all ſuch Articles, matters and things as ſhall be given you in charge. And of all other matters and things as ſhall come to your own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, touching this preſent ſervice. The King's Council, your Fellows, and your own, you ſhall keep ſecret: You ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent no perſon for Hatred or Malice; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall you leave any one unpreſented for Favour, or Affection, for Love, or Gain, or any hopes thereof; but in all things you ſhall preſent the Truth, the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100111:15"/>whole Truth, and nothing but the Tru<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to the beſt of your knowledge; ſo h<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> you God.</hi> The Tenor of the Oath plain, ſaving in thoſe words, <hi>All ſu<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> matters and things as ſhall be given <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in charge:</hi> But whenſoever a general Commiſſion of Over and Terminer is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, all Capital Offences are alwaies <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> principal matters given in charge to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Grand Jury, which is enough for <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preſent diſcourſe o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their duty: He<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> then it evidently appears, that eve<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Grand Jury is bound to enquire d<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> gently after the Truth of every thi<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for which they ſhall Indict or Preſent <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny Man: They are not only bound <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by the Eternal Law of loving the Neighbour, to be as tender of the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and good Name of every man, as of the own, and therefore to take heed to the Truth in Accuſing or Indicting any man but their expreſs Oath binds them to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> diligent in their Enquiries, that is, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> receive no ſuggeſtion of any Crime <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Truth, without examining all the C<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances about it, that fall within the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100111:15"/>knowledge; they ought to conſider the firſt Informers, and enquire as far as they can into their Aims and Pretences in their proſecutions; if Revenge or Gain ſhould appear to be their ends, there ought to be the greater ſuſpition of the Truth of their Accuſations; the Law intending all Indictments to be for the benefit of the King and of his People, as appears by the Stat. of 42 <hi>E.</hi> 3.3. Next, the Jury are bound to enquire into the matters themſelves, whereof any man is accuſed, as to the time, place, and all other circumſtances of the Fact alledged. There have been falſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers that have ſuggeſted things im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible; for inſtance, That Thirty Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Men in Arms were kept in readineſs for an Exploit, in a ſecret place, as if they could have been hid in a Chamber, or a Cabinet. The Jury ought alſo to enquire after the Witneſſes, their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and quality, their fame and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, their means of ſubſiſtence, and the occaſion whereby the Facts whereof they bear witneſs came to their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100111:16"/>Sometimes perſons of debauche<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lives and low condition, have depoſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Diſcourſes, and Treaſonable Council againſt Perſons of Honour and Virtue ſo unlikely to come to their Knowledge (if ſuch things had been) that their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of being privy to them, was ſtrong Evidence that their whole ſtory was falſe and feigned. It is alſo agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto our ancient Law and Practice and of great Conſequence in caſes <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Treaſon or Felony, that the Jury enquire after the time, when firſt the matters depoſed came to the Witneſſes know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and whether they purſued the directions of the Law in the immediat<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Diſcovery and purſuit of the Traitor o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Felon, by Hue and Cry, or otherwiſe, o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how long they concealed the ſame; their Teſtimony being of little or no value, i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they have made themſelves partake<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Crime by their voluntary Conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Neither may the Jury lawfully omi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to enquire concerning the Parties Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, of their Quality, Reputation, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100111:16"/>the manner of their Converſation, with many other Circumſtances; from whence they may be greatly helped to make right Inferences of the Falſhood, or Truth of the Crimes whereof any man ſhall be accuſed. The Jury ought to be ignorant of nothing whereof they can enquire, or be informed, that may in their underſtandings enable them to make a true Preſentment or Indictment of the matters before them.</p>
            <p>When a Grand Jury is ſworn to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire diligently after all Treaſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'tis natural and neceſſary to their buſineſs, to think of whom they ſhould enquire; and 'tis plainly and eaſily reſolved, that they ought to enquire of every man that can or will inform them; and if any kind of Treaſon be ſuggeſted to them, to have been done by any man, or number of men, their duty is the ſame in that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, as it was in the general; that is, to ſeek diligently to find the truth. 'Tis certainly inconſiſtent with their Oaths, to ſhut their Ears againſt any lawful man, that can tell them any thing relating
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100111:17"/>unto a crime in queſtion before them. No man will believe, nor can they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves think that they deſire to find an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preſent the truth of a fact, if they ſha<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> refuſe to hear any man, who ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſuch knowledge of it, or ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Circumſtances, as may be uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to diſcover it; whether that which ſhall be ſaid by the pretenders, will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Juries expectations, muſt re<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in their Judgments, when they have hea<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them. It ſeems therefore from the word of the Oath, that there is no bound or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſet (ſave their own underſtanding or Conſcience) to reſtrain them to and number or ſort of perſons of whom they are bound to enquire; they ought fir<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and principally to enquire of one another mutually, what knowledge each of the<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath of any matters in queſtion before them; the Law preſumes that ſome at lea<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of ſo many ſufficient men of a County muſt know or have heard of all notable things done there againſt the public peace; for that end the Juries are by the Law to be of the Neighborhood to the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100111:17"/>place where the crimes are committed. If the parties, and the facts whereof they are accuſed be known to the Jury, or any of them, their own knowledge will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the room of many Witneſſes. Next they ought to enquire of all ſuch Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as the Proſecutors will produce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Accuſed, they are bound to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine all fully and prudently to the beſt of their skill; every Jury Man ought to ask ſuch queſtions (by the Fore-man at leaſt) as he thinks neceſſary to reſolve any doubt that may ariſe in him, either about the fact, or the Witneſſes, or otherwiſe; if the Jury be then doubtful, they ought to receive all ſuch further Teſtimony as ſhall be offered them, and to ſend for ſuch as any of them do think able to give Teſtimony in the caſe depending.</p>
            <p>If it be asked how, or in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the Juries ſhall enquire; the anſwer is ready, according to the beſt of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings. They only, not the Judges, are ſworn to ſearch diligently to find out all Treaſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> within their charge, and they muſt and ought to uſe their own diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100111:18"/>in the way and manner of their Enquiry: No directions can legally be impoſed upon them by any Court or Judges; An honeſt Jury wil<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thankfully accept good Advice from Judges, as they are Aſſiſtants; but they are bound by their Oaths to preſent the Truth, the whole Truth, and nothing but the Truth, to the beſt of their own not the Judges, knowledge: Neither ca<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they, without breach of that Oath, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign their Conſciences, or blindly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the dictates of others; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought to receive, or reject ſuch Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, as they judge them good or bad.</p>
            <p>If the Jury ſuſpect a Combination o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Witneſſes againſt any mans Life, (which perhaps the Judges do not diſcern) and think it needful to examine them private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſeparately, the diſcretion of the Juries in ſuch a caſe, is their only, beſt and lawful guide, though the example of all Ages and Countries, in examining ſuſpected Witneſſes privately and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, may be a good direction to them.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:100111:18"/>
            <p> Nothing can be more plain and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, than the words of the Oath are to this purpoſe. The Jurors need not ſearch the Law Books, nor tumble over heaps of old Records for the explanation of them. Our greateſt Lawyers may from hence learn more certainly our ancient Law in this caſe, than from all the Books in their Stueids. The Language where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Oath is penned, is known and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by every man, and the words in it have the ſame ſignification, as they have whereſoever elſe they are uſed. The Judges (without aſſuming to themſelves a Legiſlative Power) cannot put a new ſenſe upon them, other than according to their genuine, common meaning. They cannot Magiſterially impoſe their Opinions upon the Jury, and make them forſake the direct words of their Oath, to purſue their gloſſes. The Grand In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt are bound to obſerve alike ſtrictly every part of their Oath; and to uſe all juſt and proper ways which may enable them fully to perform it; otherwiſe it were to ſay, that after men had ſworn
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100111:19"/>to enquire diligently after the Truth, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the beſt of their Knowledge, they were bound to forſake all the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and proper means which their Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings ſuggeſt for the Diſcovery of it, if it be commanded by the Judges.</p>
            <p>And therefore if they are jealous of a Combination of the Witneſſes, or that Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and Subornation hath been made uſe of, they cannot be reſtrained from asking all ſuch Queſtions, as may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the ſifting out of the Truth, nor from examining the Witneſſes privately and ſeparately;<note place="margin">Fort. D. Land. Leg. Ang. <hi>cap. 26.</hi>
               </note> leſt (as <hi>Forteſcue</hi> ſays) The ſaying of one ſhould provoke or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct others to ſay the like.</p>
            <p>Nor are the Jury tied up to enquire on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of ſuch Crimes as the Judges ſhall think fit to give them directly in charge, much leſs of ſuch Bills only as ſhall be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to them; but their Enquiry ought to extend to <hi>All other Matters and Things which ſhall come to their Knowledge, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the preſent Service.</hi> If they have ground to ſuſpect that any Accuſation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100111:19"/>them proceeds from a Conſpiracy, they are obliged by their Oaths to turn the Enquiry that way, and if they find cauſe, not only to Reject the Bills offered upon ſuch Teſtimony, but to indict ſuch Witneſſes, and all the Abettors of their Villany.</p>
            <p>They are carefully to examine what ſort of men the Witneſſes are; for 'tis a Rule in all Laws, that <hi>Turpes à Tribunalibus arcentur,</hi> Vile Perſons ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by Courts of Juſtice. Such Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes would deſtroy Juſtice inſtead of promoting it. And the Grand Jury are to take care of admitting ſuch: They may and ought (if they have no certain knowledge of them) to ask the Witneſſes themſelves of their Condition, and way of living, and all other Queſtions, which may beſt inform them what ſort of men they are. 'Tis true, it may be lawful for the Witneſſes, in many caſes, to refuſe to give anſwer to ſome demands which the Jury may make; as where it would be to accuſe themſelves of Crimes: but yet that very refuſal, or avoiding to give di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100111:20"/>Anſwers, may be of great uſe to the Jury, whoſe only buſineſs is to find out the Truth; and who will be in a good meaſure enabled to judge of the Credit of ſuch Witneſſes, as dare not clear themſelves of Crimes, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Fame, or the knowledge of ſome of the Grand Inqueſt has charged them with?</p>
            <p>If the Witneſſes which come before the Grand Jury upon an Indictment for Treaſon, ſhould diſcover upon their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, that they Concealed it a long ti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e without juſt Impediment; The preſumption of Law will be ſtrong againſt them, that no ſenſe of honeſty <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of their duty brought them at laſt to reveal it.</p>
            <p>It appears by <hi>Bracton,</hi> that ancient Writer of our Laws,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Brac. L. 3.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> n<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bet ad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liqua neg<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ia, qua<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is urgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſima, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertere, qui<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vix permittitur ei quòd retro aſpiciat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Si poſt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallum accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re velit, non e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit de Jure a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diendus.</note> that in Caſes of Treaſon the Juries were in his days ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed (as now they ought) to be ſo ſevere in their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry within what time the Witneſſes diſcovered the Treaſon after it came to their
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100111:20"/>knowledge: That if it were not evident that they reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it with as much expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as was well poſſible for them, they were not by Law no be heard as Witneſſes; It was ſcarce permitted them (ſaith he) to <hi>look back</hi> in their going; ſuch ought to be their ſpeed to make known the Treaſon. Or if in any caſe they be otherwiſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly flagitious, though they be not le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally infamous, or if they are men of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate Fortunes, ſo that the temptation of want is manifeſtly ſtrong upon them, and the reſtraint of Conſcience can be ſuppoſed to be little or none at all; what ever they ſay is (at leaſt) to be heard with extraordinary caution, if not total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rejected. In <hi>Scotland</hi> ſuch a degree of Poverty,<note place="margin">S. G. Mack<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zy, Crim. Law, <hi>lib. 26.3.</hi>
               </note> that a Witneſs cannot ſwear him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be worth Ten Pounds, is ſufficient to lay him aſide wholly in theſe high Concernments of Criminal Caſes: And in ſome other Kingdoms
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100111:21"/>to be a looſe liver is an Objection of the ſame force, againſt any produced for Witneſſes.</p>
            <p>And for the better diſcovery of the Truth of any fact in queſtion, the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of the Witneſſes, and the value of the Teſtimonies; it is the Duty of the Grand Inqueſt to be well informed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Parties indicted; of their uſual Reſidence, their Eſtates and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of living, their Companions and Friends, with whom they are accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to converſe, ſuch knowledge being neceſſary to make a good judgment up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on moſt accuſations; but moſt of all in ſuſpitions, or Indictments of ſecret Treaſons, or Treaſonable Words, where the accuſers can be of no credit, if it be altogether incredible that ſuch things as they teſtifie ſhould come to their knowledge.</p>
            <p>Sometimes the quality of the accuſed perſon may ſet him at ſuch a diſtance from the Witneſſes, that he cannot be ſuppoſed to have converſed with them familiarly, if his Wiſdom and Conduct
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100111:21"/>has been always ſuch, that it is not cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible he would truſt men ſo inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, or meer ſtrangers to him, and ſuch as are wholly uncapable to aſſiſt in the Deſign which they pretend to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover.</p>
            <p>Can the Grand Inqueſt believe ſuch Teſtimony to be of any value? Or can they avoid ſuſpecting Malice, Combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and Subornation in ſuch a caſe? or can they ſhew themſelves to be juſt, and conſcientious in their Duty, if they do not ſuſpend their Verdict until fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Enquiry, and write <hi>Ignoramus</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Bill?</p>
            <p>It is undoubtedly Law which we find reported in <hi>Stiles.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stiles Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> That <hi>Though there be Witneſſes who prove the Bill, yet the Grand Inqueſt is not bound to find it, if they ſee cauſe to the contrary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to make their Enquiry more inſtrumental and advantageous to the Execution of Juſtice, they are enjoined by their Oath to keep ſecret <hi>the King's Counſel, their fellows, and their own.</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:100111:22"/>Perhaps 'tis not ſufficiently underſtood or conſidered, what duty is enjoyned to every man of a Grand Inqueſt by this clauſe of their Oath, being ſeldom (if ever) explained to them in the general charge of the Judges at Seſſions or Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: But it is neceſſary that they ſhould apprehend what Counſel of the King is truſted with them. Certainly there is or ought to be much more of it commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to them, than is commonly thought, and in things of the greateſt conſequence. To them ought to be committed in the ſeveral Counties where any Proſecutions are begun, the firſt Informations and ſuſpitions of all Treaſons, Murders, Felonies, Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies, and other Crimes, which may ſubvert the Government, endanger, or hurt the King, or deſtroy the Lives or Eſtates of the innocent People, or any way diſquiet or diſturb the common Peace. Our Law intends the Councils of the King to be continually upon the protection and ſecurity of the People, and prevention of all their miſchiefs
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100111:22"/>and dangers by wicked, lawleſs, and injurious men And in order thereunto to be adviſing how to right his wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Subjects in general, if the publick ſafety be hazarded by Treaſons of any kind; or their Relations ſnatcht from them by Murderers, or any way deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by malicious Conſpirators in form of Law; or their Eſtates taken away by Robbery and Thieves, or the Peace bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. And for theſe ends to bring to exemplary Juſtice all offenders, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terr others from the like Wickedneſs. And until theſe Counſels of the King come to the Grand Jury, he can bring no ſuch Criminals to judgment, or to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Accuſations and Suggeſtions againſt them. Hence it becomes una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably neceſſary to reveal to the Grand Juries all that hath been diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the King or any of his Miniſters. Judges, or Juſtices, concerning any Treaſons, or other Offences, whereof any man is accuſed. And where ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion hath cauſed any to be impriſoned, all the grounds of their ſuſpitions ought
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100111:23"/>to be opened, concerning the Principals and the Acceſſories, as well before as after the fact, all the circumſtances and preſumptions that may induce a belief of their Guilt, and all notices what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, which may enable the Jury to make a more exact and effectual Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and to preſent the whole Truth. They themſelves will not only be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders againſt God by reaſon of their Oath, but ſubject to legal puniſhments, if they knowingly conceal any Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, and leave them unpreſented; and none can be innocent, who ſhall conceal from them any thing that may help and aſſiſt them in their Duty.</p>
            <p>The firſt notices of Crimes or ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Criminals by whomſoever brought in, and the intentions of ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them out, and proſecuting them le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally, are called the King's Counſel, becauſe the principal care of executing Juſtice is entruſted to him, and they are to be proſecuted at his Suit, and in his name; and ſuch proceedings are called Pleas of the Crown. From hence
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100111:23"/>may be eaſily concluded, that the Kings Counſel, which, by the Oath of the Grand Inqueſt is to be kept ſecret, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth all the perſons offered to them to be indicted, and all the matters brought in Evidence before them, all circumſtances whatſoever whereof they are informed, which may any way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the diſcovery of Offences; all intimations given them of Abettors and Encouragers of Treaſons, Felonies, or Perjuries and Conſpiracies, or of the Receivers, Harbourers, Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and Concealers of ſuch Criminals.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe the Oath which enjoins the Counſel of their Fellows, and their own to be kept, implies that they ſhall not reveal any of their perſonal knowledge concerning Offences or Offenders; nor their intentions to indict any man there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; nor any of the Propoſals and Advices amongſt them of ways to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into the truth of any matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, either about the Crimes themſelves, or the accuſers and Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, or the party accuſed, nor the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:100111:24"/>debates thereupon amongſt themſelves, nor the diverſity of opinionins any caſe before them.</p>
            <p>Certainly this Duty of ſecreſie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Kings Counſel was impoſed upon the Grand Inqueſt with great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in order to the publick good. It was intended that they ſhould have all the advantages which the ſeveral caſes will afford, to make effectual Enquiries after Criminals to offer them to Juſtice. If packs of Thieves, private Murderers, ſecret Traitors, or Conſpirators and Suborners, can get Intelligence of all that is known of their Villanies, all the parties concerned may conſult together, how to hide their crimes, and prevent ſuch further Enquiries as can be made after them; they may form Sham-Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries by agreement, that may have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of truth to miſlead and delude the Jury in their Examination, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void contradicting each other, they may remove or conceal all ſuch things as might occaſion a fuller Diſcovery of their Crimes, or become circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100111:24"/>Evidences againſt any of their Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates, if one or more of them be known or taken, or is to be indicted. There hath been Confederates in high Crimes, who have ſecured themſelves from the Juſtice done upon ſome of their Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, by their confident appearance and denial of the Fact, having been em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldened therein from their knowledge of all the grounds of ſuſpition, and all the Witneſſes examined about them and the matter of their Teſtimonies. 'Tis too well known what helps of diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole Popiſh Plot were loſt through the want of keeping ſecret the Kings Counſel therein, before the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was brought either to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or to any Grand Inqueſt; and thereby they were diſabled for the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual Execution of their Offices, and could never ſearch into the Bowels of that dangerous Treaſon in any County. But our Law having placed this great truſt of Enquiry in the prudence and faithfulneſs of the Grand Inqueſt, was careful that they might not diſable them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100111:25"/>for their own truſt, by the indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion or worſer fault of any of their own number, in revealing the Kings Counſel or their own.</p>
            <p>And as it was intended hereby to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve unto them all reaſonable helps for their bringing to light the hidden miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs that might diſturb the common Peace, ſo it was neceſſary to prevent the Flight of Criminals; if the Evidence, againſt one that is accuſed ſhould be publickly known, whether it ſhould be ſufficient for an Indictment of him, and how far it extends to others; his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates and Accomplices might eaſily have notice of their danger, and take opportunity to eſcape from Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Yet the reaſon will be ſtill more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt for keeping ſecret the accuſations and the Evidence by the Grand Inqueſt, if it be well conſidered, how uſeful and neceſſary it is for diſcovering truth in the Examinations of Witneſſes in many, if not in moſt caſes that may come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; when if by this Privacy Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes may be examined in ſuch manner
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100111:25"/>and Order, as prudence and occaſion direct; and no one of them be ſuffered to know who hath been examined be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, nor what queſtions have been asked him, nor what anſwers he hath given, it may probably be found out whether a Witneſs hath been biaſſed in his Teſtimony by Malice or Revenge, or the fear or favour of men in Power, or the love or hopes of Lucre and gain in preſent or future, or Promiſes of impunity for ſome enormous Crime.</p>
            <p>The ſimplicity of Truth in a Witneſs may appear by the natural plainneſs, eaſineſs, and directneſs of his Anſwers to whatſoever is propounded to him, by the equality of his Temper, and ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of his Anſwers to queſtions of ſeveral kinds, and perhaps to ſome that may be asked for Trial ſake only of his uprightneſs in other matters. And the Falſneſs, Malice or ill Deſign of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may be juſtly ſuſpected from his ſtudiouſneſs and difficulty in anſwering, his Artifice and cunning in what he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, not agreeable to his way of breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:100111:26"/>and parts, his reſerved, indirect, and evaſive Replies to eaſie Queſtions, his pretences of doubtfulneſs and want of remembring things of ſuch ſhort dates or ſuch Notoriety, that 'tis not credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble he could be ignorant or forgetful of them. In this manner the Truth may be evidenced to the ſatisfaction of the Jurors Conſciences, by the very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanor of the Witneſſes in their private Examinations, in as much as the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt certainty doth often ariſe from the careful obſervation and comparing of ſuch minute matters; of which a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct account is not poſſible to be giver to a Court: And for that Reaſon (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong others) the Juries are made the only abſolute Judges of their Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>Yet further their private Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may diſcover truth out of ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreement of the Witneſſes, when ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately interrogated, and every of the Grand Inqueſt ask them Queſtions for his own ſatisfaction about the matters which have come to his particular know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:100111:26"/>and this freely without Awe or Control of Judges, or diſtruſt of his own parts, or fear to be checked for asking impertinent queſtions.</p>
            <p>Conſpiracies againſt the lives of the Innocent in a form of Juſtice, have been frequently detected by ſuch ſecret and ſeparate Examination of Witneſſes. The Story of <hi>Suſanna</hi> is famous; that two of their Elders and Judges of great Credit &amp; Authority, teſtified in the open Aſſembly a malicious invention againſt her, with all the ſolemnity uſed in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital Caſes and Sentences of Death paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon her, and was ready to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted, had not wiſe <hi>Daniel</hi> cryed out in her behalf: <hi>Are ye ſuch Fools, O Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, that without Examination or Knowledge of the Truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Note that the Teſtimony given in the Aſſembly without ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, &amp; trying the Truth by circumſtances, was eſteemed</note> 
               <hi>ye <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave condemned a Daughter <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Iſrael? Return</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>again to judgment, and put <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heſe two one far from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and I will examine them:</hi> And being asked ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parately (though in publick
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:100111:27"/>the teſtimony having been ſo given before) concerning the place of the fact then in queſtion,<note place="margin">No Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or knowledg of the Truth.</note> they had not agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon that Circumſtance as they had upon their Story; and ſo their falſhood became manifeſt, one ſaying the Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery was committed under a Lentisk Tree, the other, it was under a Prime Tree: And upon that conviction of the falſe Witneſſes, the whole Aſſembly cried with a loud voice, and praiſed God. Theſe falſe Witneſſes were put to death as their Law required.</p>
            <p>We have alſo a late Inſtance of the uſefulneſs of private and ſeparate Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, in the caſe of the Lord <hi>How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard,</hi> againſt whom the Attorney Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral proſecuted an Accuſation of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the laſt Midſummer Term, before the Grand Inqueſt for <hi>Middleſex.</hi> Mrs. <hi>Fitz-Harris,</hi> and <hi>Tereſa Peacock</hi> her Maid, ſwore words of Treaſon againſt him poſitively, and agreed in every point whilſt they were together: But by the prudence of the Inqueſt, being
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:100111:27"/>put aſunder, and the Miſtriſs asked how her Maid came to be admitted to the knowledge of ſuch Matters; ſhe had an Evaſion ready, pretending her Maid to have craftily harkened behind a Wain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcot Door, and ſo heard the Treaſon. But the Maid not ſuſpecting what her Miſtriſs had ſaid, continued her firſt Story, that ſhe heard the Treaſon from the Lord <hi>Howard</hi> himſelf, and was as much truſted by him as her Miſtriſs: By this Circumſtance the falſhood and Perjury (which Mrs. <hi>Fitz-Harris</hi> hath ſince acknowledged) was diſcovered, and the ſnare for the Life of the injured Lord was broken, as is manifeſt by his liberty now obtained by Law.</p>
            <p>Witneſſes may come prepared, and tell plauſible Stories in open Court, if they know from the Proſecutor to what they muſt anſwer; and have agreed and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted each other with the tales they will tell, and have reſolved to be careful, that all their anſwers to croſs Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, may be conformable to their firſt ſtories: And if theſe relate only to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:100111:28"/>words ſpoken at ſeveral times in private to diſtinct Witneſſes, in ſuch a caſe, Evidence, if given in open Court, may ſeem to be very ſtrong againſt the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon accuſed, though there be nothing of truth in it. But if ſuch Witneſſes were privately and ſeparately examined by the Grand Inqueſt, as the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, and were to anſwer only ſuch queſtions as they thought fit, and in ſuch order as was beſt in their judgments, and moſt natural to find out the Truth of the Accuſation, ſo that the Witneſſes could not gueſs what they ſhould be asked firſt, or laſt, nor one conjecture what the other had ſaid, (which they are certain of when they know beforehand what the Proſecutor will ask in Court of every of them, and what they have reſolved to anſwer) if the Inqueſt ſhould put them out of their Road, and then compare all their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral anſwers together, they might poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly diſcern marks enough of falſhood, to ſhew that their Teſtimonies ought not to be depended upon, where life is in queſtion.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:100111:28"/>
            <p> By what is now ſaid the reaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Inſtitution of Secrecy may be diſcerned in reſpect to the diſcovery of Truth, and the protection of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent from malicious Combinations and Perjuries. Yet the ſame Secrecy of the Kings Council is no leſs neceſſary to reſerve the guilty for puniſhment; when the Evidence againſt any party accuſed is not manifeſt and full, it may be kept without prejudice under Secrecy until further Enquiry; and if ſufficient proof can afterwards be made of the Offence, an Indictment may be found by a Grand Inqueſt, and the party brought to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer it: But when the Examinations are in open Court, or the Kings Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils any other way divulged, and the Evidence is weak and leſs than the Law requires, 'tis not probable that it will be more or ſtronger, and ſhould an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment be found, and the party tried by a Petit Jury, whilſt the Evidence is not full, they muſt and ought to acquit him, and then the further proſecution for the ſame Offence is for ever barred,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:100111:29"/>though his guilt ſhould afterward be manifeſt, and confeſſed by himſelf.</p>
            <p>From hence may certainly be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that Secrecy in the Examinations and Enquiries of Gr. Juries is in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects for the Intereſt and advantage of the King. If he be concerned to have ſecret Treaſons, Felonies, and all other enormities brought to light, and that none of the Offenders ſhould eſcape Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; if the gain of their Forfeitures be thought his intereſt (which God forbid) then the firſt notices of all dangerous crimes, and wicked confederacies ought to be ſecretly and prudently purſued and ſearcht into by the Grand Inqueſt: The accuſers and Witneſſes ought not to publiſh in a Court before a multitude what they pretend to know in ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, until the diſcretion of ſo many ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men of the neighbourhood, hath firſt determined whether their teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny will amount to ſo good and full Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that it may be made publick with ſafety to the King and People in order to Juſtice. Elſe they are obliged by Oath
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:100111:29"/>to lock up in their own breaſts all the circumſtances and preſumptions of crimes, until they, or ſuch as ſhall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the ſame truſt, ſhall have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered (as they believe) Evidence e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to convict the accuſed, and then, and not before, they are to accuſe the party upon Record, by finding the Bills, (as it's uſually called.) But when Bills are offered without fatisfactory E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and they neither know nor can learn any more, they ought for the King's ſake, to indorſe <hi>Ignoramus</hi> upon them, leaſt his Honour and Juſtice be ſtained by cauſing or permitting ſuch proſecution of his People in his own name, and at his ſuit, as ſhall appear upon their Trial and Acquittal to have been frivolous, or elſe malicious deſigns upon their Lives and Fortunes.</p>
            <p>If it ſhould be ſaid, that whatſoever reaſons there are for this Oath of Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; yet it cannot deprive the King of the benefit of having the Evidence made publick, if he deſires it, and that the Grand Jury do not break their Oaths
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:100111:30"/>when the King or the Proſecutor for him will have it ſo: 'Tis not hard to ſhew that ſuch Notions have no foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in Law or Reaſon, and ſeem to come from men who have not well ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died the firſt principles of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government or of true Religion.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever hath learnt that the Kings of <hi>England</hi> were ordained for the good Government of the Kingdom in the Execution of the Laws, muſt needs know, that the King cannot lawfully ſeek any other benefit in judicial pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, than that common Right and Juſtice be done to the People accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Laws and Cuſtoms. Their Safety and Proſperity are to be the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of His continual Care and Study, that being higheſt concern. The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Honour of a Prince conſiſts in the Virtue, Multitude, Wealth and Proweſs of his People; and his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Glory is, by the excellence of his Government ſo to have encouraged Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Piety, that few or no Criminals are to be found in his Dominions. Thoſe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:100111:30"/>who have made this their principal aim, have in ſome places ſo well ſucceeded, as to introduce ſuch a Diſcipline and rectitude of manners, as rendred every man a Law unto himſelf. As it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported in the Hiſtory of <hi>Peru,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gar.</hi> de la Veg. Hiſt. de los In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas.</note> that though the Laws were ſo ſevere as to make very ſmall Crimes capital, yet it often fell out, that not one man was put to Death in a year, within the whole compaſs of that vaſt Empire.</p>
            <p>The King's only benefits in finding out and puniſhing Offenders by Courts of Juſtice are the preſervation and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Government, the protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Innocent, revenging their wrongs, and preventing further miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs by the terrors of exemplary pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments.</p>
            <p>The King is the head of Juſtice in the eſteem of our Laws, and the whole Kingdom is to expect right to be done them in his ſeveral Courts inſtituted by Law for that purpoſe. Therefore Writs iſſue out in his name in all caſes where
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:100111:31"/>relief is ſought by the Subjects: and the wrongs done to the Lives or Limbs of the People are ſaid to be done againſt the Peace of the King, his Crown and Dignity, reckoning it a diſhonour to him and his Government, that Subjects ſhould not, whilſt they live within the Law, enjoy Peace and Security. It ought to be taken for a ſcandal upon the King, when he is repreſented in a Court of Juſtice as if he were partially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, or rather inclined to deſire, that a party accuſed ſhould be found guilty, than that he ſhould be declared innocent, if he be ſo in Truth. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the King ought to wiſh in all En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries made after Treaſons, Felonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that there were none to be found in his Kingdom; and that whoſoever is accuſed, might be able to anſwer ſo well and truly for himſelf, as to ſhew the Accuſation to be erroneous or falſe, and to be acquitted of it. Something of this appears in the common Cuſtom of <hi>England,</hi> that the Clerks of the Kings Courts of Juſtice, when any man hath
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:100111:31"/>pleaded not guilty to an Indictment, prays forthwith that God would ſend him a good deliverance.</p>
            <p>The Deſtruction of every Criminal <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a loſs to a Prince, and ought to be grievous to him; in the common regard of humanity, and the more particular Relation of his Office, and the name of Father. The Kings Intereſt and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is more concerned in the Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Innocent, than in the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Guilty. This maxime can never run them into exceſſes; for it hath ever been lookt upon as a mark of great Wiſdom and Virtue in ſome Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and States, upon ſeveral occaſions <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o deſtroy all Evidences againſt Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents; and nothing is more uſual than <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o compoſe the moſt dangerous diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of Nations by Acts of general Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, which were utterly unjuſt, if it <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t were as great a crime to ſuffer the Guilty to eſcape, as to deſtroy the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent. We do not only find thoſe Princes repreſented in Hiſtory under o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Characters, who have baſely
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:100111:32"/>murthered the Innocent. but ſuch as by their Spies and Informers were too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive after the guilty; whereas none was ever blamed for Clemency, or for being too gentle Interpreters of the Laws. <hi>Tho. Trajan</hi> was an excellent Prince, endowed with all hereical Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, yet the moſt eloquent Writers, and his beſt friends found nothing more to be praiſed in his Government, than that in his time, all men might think what they plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,<note place="margin">Tacit. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Hiſt.</note> and every man ſpeak what he thought, and he had no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter way of diſtinguiſhing himſelf from his wicked Predeceſſors, than by hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the Spies and Informers, whom they had employed for the diſcovery of crimes. But if the puniſhment of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders were as univerſally neceſſary as the Protection of the Innocent, he were as much to be abhorred as <hi>Nero;</hi> and that clemency which is ſo highly praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, were to be lookt upon as the worſt of vices, and thoſe who have hitherto been taken for the beſt of Princes, were
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:100111:32"/>altogether as deteſtable as the worſt.</p>
            <p>Moreover all humane Laws were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for the preſervation of the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and for their ſakes only are pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments inflicted; that thoſe of our own Country do ſolely regard this, was well underſtood by <hi>Forteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue,</hi> who ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fort.</hi> de Laud. Leg. Ang. <hi>ch. 27.</hi>
               </note> Indeed I could <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather wiſh Twenty Evildo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to eſcape death through <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itty, than one man to be unjuſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned. Such Blood hath cried to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for Vengeance againſt Families and Kingdoms, and their utter deſtruction hath enſued. If a Criminal ſhould be acquitted by too great lenity, caution, or otherwiſe, he may be reſerved for future Juſtice from Man or God, if he doth not repent; but 'tis impoſſible that ſatisfaction or reparation ſhould be made for innocent Bloodſhed in the forms of Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Without all queſtion the Kings only juſt Intereſt in the Evidence given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the party accuſed, and in the manner of taking it, is to have the truth
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:100111:33"/>made manifeſt, that Juſtice may there upon be done impartially: And if accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations may be firſt examined in ſecret more ſtrictly and exactly, to prevent Fraud and Perjury than is poſſible to be done in open Court, (as hath before appeared) then 'tis for the Kings bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to have it ſo. And nothing done in, or by a Court about the Trial of the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, is for the King, (in the ſenſe of our Law) unleſs it ſome way conduce to juſtice in the caſe. The Witneſſes which the Proſecutor brings, are no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the King, than they tell the truth and the whole Truth impartially; and by whomſoever any others may be called, upon the Enquiry, or the Trial to be examined, if they ſincerely deliver the truth of the matters in queſtion, they are therein the Kings Witneſſes, though the accuſed be acquitted by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their Teſtimonies. If ſuch as are offered by the Attorney General to prove Treaſon againſt any man, ſhall be found to ſwear falſly, maliciouſly, or for Reward or Promiſes, though
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:100111:33"/>they depoſe poſitively facts of Treaſon againſt the accuſed, yet they are truly and properly Witneſſes againſt the King, by endeavouring to prevent Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and deſtroy his Subjects: Their Malice and Villany being confeſſed or proved, the Kings Attorny ought <hi>(ex Officio)</hi> to proſecute them in the Kings name, and at his ſuit, for their Offences againſt him in ſuch Depoſitions pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have been for him: and the legal form of the Indictment ought to be for their ſwearing falſly and maliciouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Peace of the King, his Crown and Dignity. The Proſecutors them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, notwithſtanding their big words, and aſſuming to themſelves, to be for the King, if their proſecution ſhall be proved to be malicious, or by Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy againſt the Life or Fortune of the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, they are therein againſt the King, and ought to be indicted at the King's Suit, for ſuch Proſecutions done againſt his Crown and Dignity. And if an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney General ſhould be found know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly guilty of abetting ſuch a Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:100111:34"/>his Office could not excuſe or legal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exempt him from ſuffering the villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous judgment to the deſtruction of him and his Family. 'Tis eſteemed in the Law one of the moſt odious Offences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King, to attempt in his name to deſtroy the Innocent, for whoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection he himſelf was ordained. Qu. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had the true ſenſe of our Law,<note place="margin">Co. <hi>Inſt.</hi> 3d part, p. 79.</note> when the Lord <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh,</hi> upon Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> her then Attorney's coming into her preſence, told her, this is he who proſecutes <hi>pro Domina Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> for our Lady the Queen; and ſhe ſaid, ſhe would have the form of the Records altered; for it ſhould be <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tornatus Generalis qui pro Domina ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate ſequitur.</hi> The Attorney General who proſecutes for our Lady the Truth. Whoever is truſted in that employment diſhonours his Maſter and Office, if he gives occaſion to the Subjects to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that his Maſter ſeeks other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits or advantages by Accuſations, than the common Peace and Welfare: He
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:100111:34"/>ought not to excite a jealouſie in any of their minds, that confiſcations of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates are deſigned or deſired by any of the King's Miniſters; whoſoever makes ſuch advantages to the Crown their principal aim in accuſing, are either Robbers and Murderers, (in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſenſe) in ſeeking innocent Blood for gain, or in the mildeſt Conſtruction, (ſuppoſing the Accuſation to be on good grounds) they ſhew themſelves to be of corrupt minds, and a ſcandal to their Maſter and the Government. Profit or loſs of that kind ought to have no place in judicial proceedings againſt ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Criminals, but truth is only to be regarded; and for this reaſon the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments given in Court of humane Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are in Scripture called, the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, who is the God of truth.</p>
            <p>Yet further, if any benefit to the King could be imagined by making the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to the Grand Jury publick, it could not come in competition with the Law expreſſed in their Oath; which by conſtant uninterrupted uſage, for
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:100111:35"/>ſo many Ages, hath obtained the force of Law. <hi>Bracton</hi> and <hi>Britton</hi> in their ſeveral Generations bear Witneſs, that it was then practiſed; and greater proof of it need not be ſought, than the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes that appears by the Law-Books to have been amongſt the ancient Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, whether it was Treaſon or Felony for a Grand Jury to diſcover, either who was indicted, or what Evidence was given them. The Truſt of the Grand Juries was thought ſo ſacred in thoſe Ages, and their ſecrecy of ſo great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern to the Kingdom, that whoſoever ſhould break their Oath therein, was by all thought worthy to die; only ſome would have had them ſuffer as Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, others as Felons.<note place="margin">Co. <hi>Inſtit.</hi> 3d part, p. 107. Rulls <hi>Indic.</hi> 771.</note> And at this day it is held to be a high Miſpriſion puniſhable by Fine and Impoveriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Law then having appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Evidence to be given to Grand Juries in ſecret, the King cannot deſire to have it made publick. He can do no wrong, ſaith the old Maxime, that is,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:100111:35"/>he can do nothing againſt the Law, nor is any thing to be judged for his benefit that is not warranted by Law; His Will, Commands, and deſires are therein no otherwiſe to be known: He cannot change the legal Method or manner of enquiring by Juries, nor vary in any particular caſe from the cuſtomary and general forms of judicial proceedings; he can neither abridge nor enlarge the power of Juries, no more than he can leſſen the legal Power of the Sheriffs or Judges, or by ſpecial Directions order the one how they ſhall execute Writs, and the other how they ſhall give Judgments, though theſe made by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>'Tis criminal, no doubt, for any to ſay, that the King deſires a Court of Juſtice, or a Jury, to vary from the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Law, and they ought not to be believed therein: If Letters, Writs, or other Commands ſhould come to the Judges for that purpoſe, they are bound by their Oaths not to regard them, but to hold them for null; the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:100111:36"/>Statutes of 2 <hi>E.</hi> 3.8. and 20 <hi>E.</hi> 3.1. are expreſs. That if any Writs or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments come to the Juſtices in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance of the Law, or the Execution of the ſame, or of right to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, they ſhall proceed as if no ſuch Letters, Writs, or Commands were come to them: And the Subſtance of theſe and other Statutes is inſerted into the Oath taken by every Judge; and if they be under the moſt ſolemn and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Tye in the Execution of Juſtice, to hold for nothing or none the Commands of the King under the great Seal, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Word or Deſire of an Attorney General, in the like caſe, ought to be leſs than nothing.</p>
            <p>Beſides, they are ſtrangely miſtaken, who think the King can have an Intereſt different from, or contrary unto that of the Kingdom, in the proſecution of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed Perſons: His Concernments are involved in thoſe of his People; and he can have none diſtinct from them. He is the Head of the Body Politick, and the Legal courſe of doing Juſtice, is like
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:100111:36"/>the orderly Circulation of the Blood in the Natural Bodies, by which both Head and Body are equally preſerved, and both periſh by the interruption of it.</p>
            <p>The King is obliged to the utmoſt of his Power to maintain the Law, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in its due courſe, by his Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Oath, and the Truſt thereby repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in him. In former Ages he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured not to take the Crown, unleſs he reſolved punctually to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it.<note place="margin">Brom. p. <hi>1159</hi> Mat. Paris, p. <hi>153.</hi> Hoved. p. <hi>374.</hi> Baker. p. <hi>68.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bromton</hi> &amp; others ſpeaking of the Coronation of <hi>Richard</hi> the Firſt, deliver it thus, That having firſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Oath; <hi>Deinde indutus Mantel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, ductus eſt ad Altare, &amp; conjuratus ab Archiepiſcopo, &amp; prohibitus ex parte Dei, ne hunc Honorem ſibi aſſumat, niſi in mente habeat tenere Sacramenta &amp; Vota quae ſuperius fecit. Et Ipſe reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, ſe per Dei auxilium omnia ſupra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicta obſervaturum bona fide. Deinde cepit Coronam de Altari, &amp; tradidit eam Archiepiſcopo, qui poſuit eam ſuper
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:100111:37"/>caput Regis, &amp; ſic Coronatus Rex, ductus eſt ad ſedem ſuam.</hi> Afterward cloathed with the Royal Robe, he is led to the Altar, and conjured by the Archbiſhop, and forbid in the Name of God, not to aſſume that Honour, unleſs he intended to keep the Oaths and Vows he had before made; and he anſwered, by God's help he would ſaithfully obſerve all the Premiſes: And then he took the Crown from off the Altar, and delivered it to the Archbiſhop, who put it upon the King's head; and the King thus Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is led unto his Seat. The violation of which Truſt cannot but be as well a wound unto their Conſciences as bring great prejudice upon their Perſons and Affairs.</p>
            <p>The Common Law that exacts this, doth ſo far provide for Princes, That having their minds free from cares of preſerving themſelves they may reſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that no Acts, Words or Deſigns, that may bring them into danger, can be concealed from the many hundreds of men, who by the Law are appointed
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:100111:37"/>in all parts of the Kingdom, watchfully to take care of the King; and are ſo far concerned in his ſafety, that they can hope no longer to enjoy their own Lives and Fortunes in peace, than they can preſerve him, and the good Order which according to the Laws he is to uphold.</p>
            <p>It is the Joynt Intereſt of King and People that the Antient Rules of doing Juſtice be held ſacred and inviolable; and they are equally concerned in cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſtrict Inquiries to be made into all Evidences given againſt ſuſpected, or accuſed Perſons, that the Truth may be diſcovered; and ſuch as dare to diſturb the Publick Peace by breaking the Laws, may be brought to puniſhment. And the whole courſe of Judicial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in Criminal Cauſes, ſhews that the People is therein equally concerned with the King, whoſe Name is uſed. This is the ground of that diſtinction which Sir <hi>Ed. Coke</hi> makes between the Proceedings in Pleas of the Crown, and Actions for wrongs done to the King
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:100111:38"/>himſelf.<note place="margin">Co. 3d. Inſt. pag. <hi>136.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>In Pleas of the Crown, or other common of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, nuſances,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>principally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning others, or the Publick, there the King by Law muſt be appriſed by Indictment, Preſentment, or other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Record; but the King may have an Action for ſuch wrong as is done to himſelf, and whereof none other can have an Action but the King, without being appriſed by Indictment, Preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or other matter of Record, as a</hi> Quare impedit, Quare incumbravit, <hi>a Writ of Attaint, of Debt, Detinue of Ward, Eſcheat, Scire fac. pur repealer patent,</hi> &amp;c. Unto which every man muſt anſwer: But no man can be brought to anſwer for Publick Crimes at the King's Suit otherwiſe than by Indictment of a Grand Jury.</p>
            <p>The whole Courſe of doing Juſtice upon Crimina's, from the beginning of the proceſs, unto the Execution of the Sentence, is, and ever was eſteemed to be the Kingdoms concernment, as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced by the frequent Complaints
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:100111:38"/>made in Parliament, that Capital Offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers were pardon'd to the Peoples damage and wrong. In the 13 <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. it is ſaid, that the King hearing the grievous Complaints of his Commons in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of the outragious miſchiefs which happened unto the Realm, for that Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Murders, and Rapes of Women, be commonly done, and committed, and the more becauſe Charters of pardon had been eaſily granted in ſuch caſes; And thereupon it was enacted, that no pardon for ſuch crimes ſhould be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, unleſs the ſame were particularly ſpecified therein, and that if a pardon were otherwiſe granted for the death of a man, the Judges ſhould notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enquire by a Grand Jury of the Neighbourhood concerning the death of every ſuch perſon, and if he were found to have been wilfully murdered, ſuch Charter of Pardon to be diſallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and proviſions were made by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing grievous Fines upon every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, according to his Degree and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, or Impriſonment, who ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:100111:39"/>to ſue to the King for any pardons of the aforeſaid crimes, and that ſuch perſons might be known to the whole Kingdom, their names were to be upon ſeveral Records. The like had been done in many Statutes made by ſeveral Parliaments, as in the 6 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1.9. the 2 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.2. the 10 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.2. and the 14 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.15. wherein it was acknowledged by the King in Parliament, <hi>That the Oath of the Crown had not been kept, by reaſon of the Grant of Pardons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the aforeſaid Statutes; and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted that any ſuch Charter of Pardon, from thenceforth granted againſt the Oath of his Crown and the ſaid Statutes, the ſame ſhould be holden for none.</hi> In the 27 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.2. It is further provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for preventing the Peoples damage by ſuch pardons. <hi>That from thenceforth in every Charter of Pardon of Felony, which ſhall be granted at any mans ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, the ſaid ſuggeſtion, and the name of him that maketh the ſuggeſtion, ſhall be compriſed in the ſame Charter, and if after the ſame ſuggeſtion be found un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:100111:39"/>the Charter ſhall be diſallowed and holden for none: And the Juſtices before whom ſuch Charter ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, ſhall enquire of the ſame ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and that as well of Charters granted before this time, as of Charters which ſhall be granted in time to come, and if they find them untrue, then they ſhall diſallow the Charter ſo alledged, and ſhall moreover do as the Law de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have Parliaments from time to time declared, that the Offences againſt <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Crown are againſt the publick wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are, and that Kings are obliged by <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir Oath and Office to cauſe Juſtice to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e done upon Traitors and Felons <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or the Kingdoms ſake; according to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ancient common Law, declared by <hi>Magna Charta</hi> in theſe <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ords: <hi>Nulli negabimus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">9 <hi>Hen.</hi> 3.29.</note> 
               <hi>nulli vendemus, nulli dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>remus Juſtitiam.</hi> We will ſell to no <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an, we will not deny or defer to any <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an either Juſtice or Right.</p>
            <p>And as the publick is concerned, that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:100111:40"/>the due and legal Methods be obſerved in the Proſecution of Offenders, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe doth the ſecurity of every ſingle man in the Nation depend upon it: No man can aſſure himſelf he ſhall not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of the higheſt crimes. Let a mans Innocence and prudence be what it will, yet his moſt inoffenſive Words and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are liable to be miſconſtrued, and he may, by Subornation and Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, have things laid to his charge, of which he is no ways guilty. Who can ſpeak or carry himſelf with that circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, as not to have his harmleſs Words or Actions wreſted to another ſence than he intended? Who can be ſecure from having a Paper pur into his Pockets, or laid in his houſe, of which he ſhall know nothing till his Accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Hiſtory affords many Examples of the deteſtable practices in this kind of wicked Court Paraſites, among which one may ſuffice for Inſtance, out of <hi>Polibius</hi> an approved Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Polib.</hi> lib. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Hermes</hi> a powerful Favourite, under <hi>Antiochus</hi> the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:100111:40"/>but a man noted to be a favourer of Liars, was made uſe of againſt the innocent and brave <hi>Epigenes:</hi> He had long watcht to kill him, for that he found him a man of great Eloquence and Valour, having alſo favour and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with the King: He had unjuſtly but unſucceſsfully accuſed him of Treaſon by falſe gloſſes put upon his faithful ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice given to the King in open Council; <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his not prevailing, he by artifice got him put out of his Command, and to retire from Court; which done, he laid <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Plot againſt him, with the help and Counſel of (one of his Complices) <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and writing Letters as if they had been ſent from <hi>Molon,</hi> (who was then in open Rebellion againſt his Prince <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or fear, amongſt other Reaſons, of the Cruelty and Treachery of <hi>Hermes</hi>) and corrupted one of <hi>Alexis</hi>'s Servants with <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reat Promiſes, who went to <hi>Epigenes,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o thruſt the Letters ſecretly amongſt <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is other Writings, which when he had <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one, <hi>Alexis</hi> came ſuddenly to <hi>Epigenes,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emanding of him, if he had received
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:100111:41"/>any Letter from <hi>Molon:</hi> and when he ſaid he had none, the other ſaid, he was confident he ſhould find ſome; wherefore entring the Houſe to ſearch, he found the Letters, and taking this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, ſlew him, [leſt if the Fact had been duly examined, the Conſpiracy had been diſcovered.] Theſe things happening thus, the King thought that he was juſtly ſlain; in this manner the worthy <hi>Epigenes</hi> ended his days: But this great mans deſigns did not reſt here; for within a while heightened with ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, he ſo arrogantly abuſed His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Authority, as he grew dangerous to the King himſelf, as well as to thoſe about him; inſomuch as <hi>Antiochus</hi> was ſorced for that he hated and feared <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes,</hi> to take away his Life by Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem, thereby to ſecure himſelf. By theſe, and a thouſand other ways, the moſt unblemiſht Innocence may be brought into the greateſt dangers. Since then every man is thus eaſily ſubject to queſtion, and what is one mans caſe this day, may be another man's to morrow
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:100111:41"/>it is undoubtedly every mans concern, to ſee (as far as in him lies) in every caſe, that the accuſed Perſon may have the benefit of all ſuch proviſions, as the Law hath made for the defence of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence and Reputation.</p>
            <p>Now to this end there is nothing ſo neceſſary as the ſecret and ſeparate exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of Witneſſes, for though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps (as hath been already obſerved) it may be no very difficult thing for ſeveral perſons, who are permitted to diſcourſe with each other freely, and to hear, or be told what each of their fellows had been asked and anſwered, to agree in one ſtory, eſpecially if the Jury may not ask what queſtions they ſhall think it for the ſatisfaction of their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; but that they ſhall be ſo far under the correction and cenſure of the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udges, as to have the queſtions which they put, called by them trifles, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, and unfit for the Witneſſes <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſpeak to; yet if they be examined a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>art, with that due care of ſifting out <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll the Circumſtances which the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:100111:42"/>where every man of the Jury is at full liberty to enquire into any thing for his clearer information, and that with what deliberation they think fit, and all this be done with that ſecrecy which the law commands; it will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt impoſſible for a man to ſuffer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a falſe Accuſation.</p>
            <p>Nor has the Law been leſs careful for the Reputation of the Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> than for their Lives and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and this ſeems to be one reaſon why in criminal Caſes, a man ſhall not be brought to an open legal Trial by a Petit Jury, till the Grand Jury have firſt found the Bill: The Law having entruſted the Grand Inqueſt in a ſpecial manner with their good names; they are therefore not only to enquire whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the fact that is laid, was done by the party accuſed, but into the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances thereof too, whether it were done traiterouſly, feloniouſly, or mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> according to the manner charged, which Circumſtances are not barely matter of form, but do conſtitute
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:100111:42"/>the very eſſence of the Crime; and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the Credit of the Witneſſes, and that of the party accuſed, and unleſs they find both the Fact proved upon him, and ſtrong preſumptions of ſuch aggravating circumſtances attending it, as the Law requires in the ſpecification of ſuch Crime, and likewiſe are ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the credibility of the Witneſſes; they ought not to expoſe the Subject to an open Trial in the face of the County, to a certain loſs of his Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and hazard of his Life and Eſtate. Moreover ſhould this practice of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Examination prevail, and the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors Oath of Secrecy continue, how par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial and unequal a thing would it be to declare that to all the World, which will blaſt a mans good name, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly cenceal what they may know tending to his Juſtification: To exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Witneſſes (perhaps ſuborned) cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly prepared, and have Evidence dreſſed up with all the advantages that Lawyers wits can give it, of the foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Crimes a man can be guilty of, and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:100111:43"/>this given before ſome thouſands againſt him, and yet for the ſame Court to ſwear thoſe, whom the Law makes Judges in the caſe, not to reveal one word of thoſe reaſons, which have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied their Conſciences of his Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence. What is this, but an Artifice of ſlandring men (it may be) of the moſt unſpotted cnnverſation, and of abuſing Authority, not ſo much to find men guilty, as to make them infamous? After this Ignominy is fixed, what Judgment can the Auditors (and from them the World) make, but of high pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of guilt in the party accuſed, and Perjury in the Jury.</p>
            <p>This courſe, if it ſhould be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, muſt needs be of moſt dangerous conſequence to all ſorts of men; it will both ſubject every one without relief to be defamed, and fright the beſt and moſt conſciencious men, from ſerving on Grand Juries, which is a moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary part of their duty. Now ſince there is in our Government (as in every one that is well conſtituted there ought
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:100111:43"/>to be) great liberty of Accuſation, that no man may be encouraged to do ill through hopes of impunity, if by this means a Method be opened, for the blaſting the moſt innocent mans honour, and deterring the moſt honeſt from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Judges, what remains, but that every mans Reputation, which is moſt dear unto ſuch as are good, is held pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cariouſly, and it will be in the power of great men to pervert the Laws, and take away whoſe Life and Eſtate they pleaſe, or at leaſt to faſten imputations of the moſt deteſted crimes upon any, whom, for ſecret reaſons they have a mind to defame. The conſequences of which ſcandal, as they are very miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous to every man, ſo in a Trading Country in a more eſpecial manner, to all who live by any vocation of that kind.</p>
            <p>The greateſt part of Trade is driven upon credit, moſt men of any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Employment, dealing for much more than they are truly worth, and every
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:100111:44"/>mans credit depends as well upon his behaviour to the Government he lives under, as upon his private honeſty in his tranſactions between man and man; ſo that the ſuſpicion only of his being obnoxious to the Government is enough to ſet all his Creditors upon his back, and put a Stop to all his Affairs, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps to his utter ruine. What expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and violence will they all uſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their debts, when he ſhall be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly charged with ſuch crimes as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Life and Eſtate? Though there ſhould not be one word of the Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion true, yet they knowing the charge and the ſeeming proofs in the Court, and the conſequences of it, and not being acquainted with the truth, as it appears to the Jury, ſelf intereſt will make his Creditors to draw in their ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, which is no more than a new contrivance, under colour of Law, of undoing honeſt men.</p>
            <p>If to prevent any of theſe miſchiefs the Jury ſhould diſcover their fellows and their own Counſel, as the Court by
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:100111:44"/>publick Examination doth, it would not only be a wilful breach of their Oath, but a betraying of the truſt which the Law has repoſed in them, for the ſecurity of the Subject: For to ſubject the reaſons of their Verdicts upon Bills to the cenſure of the Judges, were to diveſt themſelves of the Power which the Law has given them, for moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant conſiderations, without account or control, and to intereſt thoſe in it, whom the Law has not in this caſe truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſo by degrees, the courſe of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in one of the moſt material parts may be changed, and a fundamental ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of our Liberty and Property in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly loſt. On the other hand, if for fear of being unworthily reproached as <hi>Ignoramus</hi> Jury-Men, obſtinate fellows, that obſtruct Juſtice, and diſſerve the King, the Grand Jury ſhall ſuffer the Judges, or the Kings Counſel to prevail with them, to indorſe <hi>Billa vera,</hi> when their Conſciences are not ſatified in the truth of the Accuſation, they act di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt their Oaths, oppreſs the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:100111:45"/>innocent whom they ought to protect; as far as in them lies, ſubject their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, themſelves, and poſterity to Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary powers, pervert the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of juſtice, and overthrow the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which is inſtituted for the obtaining of it, and ſubſiſts by it.</p>
            <p>This ſeems to be the greateſt Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that can be committed againſt the whole Kingdom, and threatens ruine unto every man in private in it. None can be ſafe againſt authorized Malice, and notwithſtanding the care of our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, Rapine, Murther, and the worſt of crimes, may be advanced by the formality of Verdicts, if Grand Juries be overawed, or not ſuffered to enquire into the Truth, to the ſatisfaction of their Conſciences. Every man whilſt he lives innocently, doth, under God, place his hopes of ſecurity in the Law, which can give no protection, if its due courſe be ſo interrupted, that frauds cannot be diſcovered, Witneſſes may as well favour offenders, as give falſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt the guiltleſs, and if they, by
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:100111:45"/>hearing what each other ſaith, are put into a way of concealing their villainous deſigns, there can be no legal Revenge of the crimes already committed. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by their impunity will be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to do the like: And every qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et minded perſon will be equally expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed unto private injuries, and ſuch as may be done unto him, under the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Law. No man can promiſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelf any ſecurity for his Life or goods, and they who do not ſuffer the u<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>moſt violences in their own perſons, may do it in their Children, Friends, and neareſt Relations, if he be deprived of the remedies that the Law ordains, and forced to depend upon the Will of a Judge, who may be (and perhaps we may ſay) are too often corrupted, or ſwayed by their own Paſſions, Intereſts, or the Impulſe of ſuch as are greater than they. This miſchief is aggravated by a commonly received Opinion, that whoſoever ſpeaks againſt an accuſed perſon is the Kings Witneſs, and the worſt of men, in their worſt deſigns do
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:100111:46"/>uſually ſhelter themſelves under that name, whereas he only is the Kings Witneſs, who ſpeaks the truth, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be for or againſt him that is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed. As the Power of the King is the Power of the Law, he can have no other intention than that of the Law, which is to have Juſtice impartially ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred; and as he is the Father of his People, he cannot but incline ever to the gentleſt ſide, unleſs it be poſſible for a Father to delight in the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or deſire to enrich himſelf by the confiſcation of his Childrens Eſtates. If the moſt wicked Princes have had different thoughts, they have been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to diſſemble them. We know of none worſe than <hi>Nero,</hi> but he was ſo far from acknowledging, that he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red any mans condemnation, that he looked upon the neceſſity of ſigning War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants for the execution of Malefactors,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sne. Vit. Ner.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam neſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem letteras.</note> as a burthen, and rather wiſhed he had not learnt to write, than to be obliged to do it. They who by
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:100111:46"/>ſpreading ſuch barbarous errours, would create unto the King, an intereſt different from that of his People which he is to preſerve, whilſt they pretend to ſerve him in deſtroying of them, they deprive him of his honour and dignity; Juſtice is done in all places, in the name of the chief Magiſtrate, it being preſumed, that he doth em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace every one of his Subjects with equal tenderneſs, until the guilty are by legal proofs diſcriminated from the Innocent, and amongſt us the Kings name may be uſed in civil caſes, as well as criminal: But it is as impoſſible for him rightly to deſire I ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for killing a man whom I have not killed, or a Treaſon that I have not committed, as that my Land ſhould be unjuſtly taken from me by a judgment in his Bench, or I ſhould be condemned to pay a debt that I do not owe.</p>
            <p>In both caſes we ſue unto him for Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and demand it as our right. We are all concerned in it, publickly, and privately, and the King, as well as all
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:100111:47"/>the Officers of Juſtice, are by their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Oaths, obliged in their reſpective capacities to perform it. They are bound to give their aſſiſtance to find out Offenders, and the Kings Attorney is by his Oath to proſecute them, if he be required; and he is not only the Kings ſervant in ſuch caſes, but the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; or rather, cannot otherwiſe ſerve the King, than by ſeeing Juſtice done in the Nation. Whenſoever any man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives an injury in his Perſon, Wife, Children, Friends, or goods, the King is injured, in as much as he is by his Office to prevent ſuch miſchief, and ought to be concerned in the Welfare of every one of his Subjects; but the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to whom the injuries are done, are the immediate ſufferers, and the proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution is principally made, that they may be repared or revenged, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther innocent perſons ſecured by the puniſhment of Offenders, in which the King can be no otherwiſe concerned, than as he is to ſee his Office faithfully performed, and his People protected.
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:100111:47"/>The Kings ſuit therefore is in the behalf of his People, yet the Laws leave unto euery man a Liberty, in caſe of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Murthers, Rapes, Robberies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to ſue in the Kings name, and crave his aid, or by way of appeal in his own. The ſame Law looks upon Felons, or Traitors as publick Enemies, and by authorizing every one to purſue or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend them, teacheth us, that every man, in his place, ought to do it. The ſame Act whereby one, or a few are injured, threatneth all, and every mans private intereſt ſo concurs with that of the publick, that all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the exact preſervation of the Method preſcribed by the Law, for the impartial inquiſition after ſuſpected Offenders, and moſt tender care of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving ſuch as are innocent. As this cannot poſſibly be effected without ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and ſeparate examinations, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding of them is no leſs, than to change the Courſe, which is enjoyned by Law, confirmed by cuſtom, and grounded upon reaſon and Juſtice. If
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:100111:48"/>on the other ſide any man believe, that ſuch as in the Kings name proſecute ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Delinquents, ought only to try how they may bring them to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, he may be pleaſed to conſider, that all ſuch perſons ought, according unto Law, to produce no Witneſs whom they do not think to be true: No Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence which they do not believe good, nor can conceal any thing that may ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the accuſed. No trick or artifice can be lawfully uſed to deceive a Grand Jury, or induce them to find or reject a Bill, otherwiſe than as they are led by their own Conſciences. All Lawyers were antiently ſworn to put no deceit upon the Courts for their Clients ſake, and there are Statutes ſtill in force to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them, if they do it, but there is an eternal obligation upon ſuch as are of Counſel againſt perſons accuſed of crimes, not to uſe ſuch arts as may bring the innocent to be condemned, and thereby pervert that which is not called the judgment of man, but of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe man renders it in the ſtead, and by
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:100111:48"/>the Commandment of God, ſuch practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes exalt the Juriſdiction of Tribunals, but infect and pollute them with that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Blood, which will be their over-throw: And leaſt of all, can it be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a ſervice to the King, ſince none could ever ſtand againſt the cry of it. This is neceſſarily implyed in the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney general his Oath, to ſerve the King in his Kingly Office, wherein the Law preſumes he can do no wrong: But the greateſt of all wrongs, and that which hath been moſt deſtructive unto Thrones, is by Fraud to circumvent and deſtroy the Innocent: This is to turn a legal King into a <hi>Nimrod,</hi> a Hunter of Men: This is not to act the part of a Father or a Shepherd, who is ready to lay down his Life for his Sheep, but ſuch as the Pſalmiſt complains of, who eat up the People as if they eat Bread: <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebel</hi> did perhaps applaud her own Wit, and think ſhe had done a great Service to the King, by finding out men of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial,</hi> Judges, and Witneſſes to bring <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both</hi> to be ſtoned; but that unregarded
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:100111:49"/>Blood was a Canker, or the Plague of Leproſie in his Throne and Family, which could not be cured but by its overthrow and extinction. But if the Attorney General cannot ſerve the King by abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Juries, and ſubverting the Innocent, he can as little gain an advantage to himſelf by falſifying his Oath, by the true meaning whereof he is to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Juſtice impartially, and the Eternal Divine Law would annul any Oath or Promiſe that he ſhould have taken to the contrary, even though his Office had obliged him unto it.</p>
            <p>The like Obligation lies upon Jurors not to ſuffer themſelves to be deluded, or perſuaded, that the Judges, Kings Council, or any others can diſpenſe with that Oath, or any part of it, which they have taken before God unto the whole Nation; nor to think that they can ſwerve from the Rules ſet by the Law without a damnable breach of it, The power of relating, or diſſolving Conſcientious Obligations, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in the Pope, makes a great part
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:100111:49"/>of the <hi>Roman</hi> Superſtition; and that grand Impoſtor could never corrupt Kingdoms and Nations to their deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and the Eſtabliſhment of his Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, until he had brought them to believe he could diſpenſe with Oaths, taken by Kings unto their Subjects, and by Subjects to their Kings; nor impoſe ſo extravagant an Errour upon either, until he had perſuaded them he was in the place of God. It is hard to ſay how the Judges or Kings Council can have the ſame Power, unleſs it be upon the ſame Title; but we may be ſure they may as well diſpenſe with the whole Oath as any part of it, and can have no pretence unto either, unleſs they have the Keys of Heaven and Hell in their keeping: It is in vain to ſay, the King as any other man may remit the Oath taken unto and for himſelf; He is not a party for himſelf, but in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of his People, and cannot diſpoſe of their Concernments without their Conſent, which is given only in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:100111:50"/>
            <p> The Kings Council ought to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, they are in criminal Caſes of Council unto every man in the Kingdom; It is no ways referred unto the Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Judges, or unto them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that ſecrecy enjoined by Law, be profitable unto the King or Kingdom; They muſt take the Law as it is, and render Obedience unto it, until it be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by the Power that made it. To this end the Judges by Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>viz.</hi> 18 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. and 20 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. are ſworn to ſerve the People, <hi>Ye ſhall ſerve our Lord the King and his People in the Office of Juſtice,</hi> &amp;c, <hi>Ye ſhall deny to no man common Right by the Kings Letters, nor no other mans; nor for no other cauſe; and in default thereof in any point, they are to forfeit their Bodies, Lands and Goods.</hi> This proves them to be the Peoples Servants as well as the Kings.</p>
            <p>Further by the expreſs words of the Commiſſions of Oyer and Terminer, they are required to <hi>aſſiſt every man that ſuffers injury, and make diligent inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:100111:50"/>after all manner of falſhoods, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, offences, and wrongs done to any man, and thereupon to do Juſtice accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law:</hi> ſo that in the whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in order unto Tryal, and in the Tryals themſelves, the Thing principally intended, which ſeveral perſons are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally in their capacities obliged to purſue, is, the diſcovery of Truth: The witneſſes are to depoſe <hi>the Truth, the whole Truth, and Nothing but the Truth:</hi> Thereupon the Council for the King are to proſecute: The Grand Jury to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: and the Petit Jury to try: Theſe are ſeveral Offices, but all to the ſame End; Tis not the Priſoner, but the Crime that is to be purſued; This pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily, the Offender but by conſequence; and therefore ſuch Courſes muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as may diſcover that, and not ſuch as may enſnare him: When the Offence is found, the impartial Letter of the Law gives the Doom; and the Judges have no ſhare in it, but the pronouncing of it: Till then the Judges are only to preſide, and take Care, that every man
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:100111:51"/>elſe, who is employed in this neceſſary Affair, do his duty according to Law. So that upon reſult of the whole tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaction impartial Juſtice may be done, Either to the Acquittal, or condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Priſoner.</p>
            <p>Hereby it is manifeſt why the Judges are obliged by Oath, To <hi>Serve the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as well as the King:</hi> And by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, To <hi>Serve every One that Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers Injuries.</hi> As they are to See that Right be done to the King, &amp; His Injur'd Subjects in diſcovering of the Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent; So they are to be of Council with the Priſoner, whom the Law ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth may be ignorant as well as innocent; and therefore has provided, that the Court ſhall be of Council for him, and as well inform him of what Legal advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages the Law allows him, as to reſolve any point of Law when he ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it to them; And it ſeems to be upon the preſumption of this ſteady impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality in the Judges, (thus obliged by all that is held Sacred before God and man to be unbyaſſed) that the Priſoner
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:100111:51"/>hath no Council; for if the Court faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully perform their duty, the Accuſed can have no wrong, or hardſhip, and therefore needs no Adviſer.</p>
            <p>Now ſuppoſe a man perfectly inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and in ſome meaſure knowing in the Law, ſhould be accuſed of Treaſon or Felony; If the Judges ſhall deny un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Grand Jury the Liberty of exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining any witneſſes, except in open Court, where nothing ſhall be offered that may help to clear the Priſoner, but every Thing aggravated, that gives co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour for the Accuſation; ſuch Perſons only produced, as the Kings Council, or the proſecutors ſhall think fit to call, of whoſe Credit alſo the Jury muſt not inquire, but ſhall be controll'd and brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beaten in asking Queſtions, of ſuch unknown witneſſes, for their own Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, if they have any Tendency to diſcover the Infamy of theſe witneſſes, or the Falſhood of their Teſtimony; How can Innocence ſecure any Man from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arraigned?</p>
            <p>And if the Oath of the Judges ſhould
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:100111:52"/>be as much forgotten in the further Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings upon the Tr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al, where in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Treaſon the Priſoner ſhall have all the Kings Council (commonly not the moſt unlearned) prepared with ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died ſpeeches, and arguments, to make him black, and odious, and to Strein all his words, and to alledge them for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of his guilt: If then all his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Papers, and Notes to help his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory in his Plea, and defence, ſhall be taken from him by the Gaoler, or the Court, and given to his Proſecutors; And all Advice &amp; Aſſiſtance from Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils or friends, and his neareſt Relations ſhall be denied him, &amp; none ſuffered by word or writing to inform him of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency, or honeſty, or the Partiality or malice of the Pannels returned (whom the Law allows him to Challenge or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, either peremptorily, or for good Reaſons offered;) ſhould he be thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of all the good proviſions of the Law for his ſafety, To what Frauds, Perjuries, &amp; Subornations is not he, and every man Expoſed, who may be accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed?
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:100111:52"/>What Deceits may there not be put upon Juries? and what Probability is there of finding ſecurity in Innocence? What an admirable Execution would this be of their Commiſſion, To <hi>make di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Inquiſition after all manner of Falſhoods, Deceipts, wrongs and Frauds, and thereupon to do Juſtice according to Law?</hi> When at the ſame Time; if ſo Managed, a Method would be introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of ruining and deſtroying any Man in the form of Juſtice. Such practices would be the higheſt diſhonour to the King imaginable, whoſe name is uſed, and ſo far Miſrepreſent the Kingly Office, as to make that appear, to have been Erected to vex and deſtroy the People, which was intended, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to help and preſerve them.</p>
            <p>The Law ſo far abhors ſuch proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that it intends, that every Man ſhould be ſtrictly bound, to be Exactly juſt, in their ſeveral Imployments, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Execution of Juſtice. The Sergeant, of the Kings Council (Sir <hi>George Jeffrys,</hi> among the reſt) who
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:100111:53"/>proſecute in the King's name, and are conſulted in the forming bills of Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and advice about the witneſſes and their Teſtimonies againſt the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed; Theſe (if they would remember it) when they are made Sergeants, take an Oath (<hi>Cokes</hi> 2d Inſtitutes Pag. 214.) <hi>as well &amp; truly to ſerve the People</hi> (whereof the party accuſed is one) <hi>as the King himſelf and to miniſter the Kings matters duely and truely after the courſe of the Law to their Cunning;</hi> Not to uſe their Cunning &amp; Craft to hide the Truth and deſtroy the accuſed if they can.</p>
            <p>They are alſo obliged by the Statute of <hi>Weſtm.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 29. To put no manner of Deceit or Colluſion upon the Kings Court, nor ſecretly to conſent to any ſuch Tricks as may abuſe or beguile the Court, or the party, be it in Cauſes Civil or Criminal: And it is ordained that if any of them be convicted of ſuch pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, he ſhall be impriſoned for a year, &amp; never be heard to plead again in any Court; and if the Miſchievous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:100111:53"/>of their Treacheries be great, they are Subject to further and greater puniſhments. Our Auntient Law Book called <hi>the Mirror of Juſtice, Cap.</hi> 2. Sect. 4. ſays, <hi>That every Sergeant Pleader is chargeable by his Oath, not to maintain or defend any wrong or Falſhood to his Knowledge, but ſhall leave his Client when he ſhall perceive the wrong intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him: Alſo that he ſhall not move or proffer any falſe Teſtimony, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to any Lyes Deceits or Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions whatſoever in his pleadings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As a further Security unto the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple againſt all Attempts upon their Laws, Exemplary Juſtice hath been done, in ſeveral Ages, upon ſuch Judges, and Juſticiaries, as through Corruption, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion unto unjuſt Commands, or any other Siniſter conſideration, have dared to ſwerve from them: The puniſhments of theſe wicked Men remain upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, as Monuments of their Infamy to be a Terror unto all that ſhall ſucceed them. In the Reign of the <hi>Saxons</hi> the moſt notable Example was given by
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:100111:54"/>King <hi>Alfred,</hi> who caus'd above forty Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to be hanged in a Short Space, for ſeveral wrongs done to the People, as is related in <hi>the Mirror of Juſtice:</hi> Some of them ſuffered for impoſing upon Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and forcing them to give Verdicts according to their will; And one as it ſeems, had taken the Conſidence to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine a Jury, that he might find which of them would Submit to his will, and Setting aſide him who would nor, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned a Man upon the Verdict of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>Since the Coming in of the <hi>Normans,</hi> our Parliaments have not been leſs ſevere againſt ſuch Judges, as have ſuffered the courſe of Juſtice to be perverted, or the Rights and Liberties of the People to be invaded: In the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the 1ſt <hi>Anno</hi> 1289. The Parliament find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That all the Judges (except Two) had ſwerv'd from their duty, condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to ſeveral puniſhments accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto their Crimes, As Baniſhment, Perpetual Impriſonment,<note place="margin">Ex Chron. Anno <hi>10</hi> Ed. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> or the Loſs of all their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:100111:54"/>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Their Particular Offences are ſpecified in a ſpeech made by the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> in Parliament. They had broken <hi>Magna Charta;</hi> Incit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the King againſt his People; Violated the Laws under pretence of expounding them; And impudently preſumed to prefer their own Councils to the King, before the Advices of Parliament, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the ſpeech, &amp;c. Hereunto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>next.</p>
            <p>The like was done in <hi>Ed.</hi> the 2d Time when <hi>Hugh De Spencer</hi> was charged for having prevailed with the King to break his Oath to the People, in doing Things againſt the Law by his own Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Edward</hi> the 3d. Time Judge <hi>Thorpe</hi> was hanged for having in the like manner brought the King to break his Oath:<note place="margin">Dan. Hiſtory p. <hi>260, 261.</hi>
               </note> And the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Reign of that great King affords many Inſtances of the like nature, amongſt which the puniſhment of Sr. <hi>Henry Green</hi> and Sr. <hi>William Skipwith,</hi> deſerve to be obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:100111:55"/>and put into an Equal rank with thoſe of his brave and victorious Grand-father.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Richard</hi> the Second's Time,<note place="margin">See all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hiſtories of <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingham, Fabian, Speed,</hi> &amp;c. in the 11 and 21 years of <hi>Richard</hi> the 2d.</note> Eleven of the Judges, forgetting the dreadful Puniſhments of their Predeceſſors, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed malicious Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt Law, and gave falſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations of our Antient Laws to the King, thereby to bring many of his moſt Eminent, &amp; worthieſt Subjects, to ſuffer as Traytors at his Will: Subjected the Authority, and very being of Parliaments to his abſolute pleaſure, And made him believe, that all the Laws lay in his own breaſt: Hereupon ſentence of death paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon them; and tho upon their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and confeſſing, they had been ſwayed by fear, and threatnings from the King, Two only were Executed, all the others, were for ever baniſhed, as unworthy to enjoy the benefit of that Law, which they had ſo perfidiouſly, and baſely betrayed.</p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:100111:55"/>
            <p> It were an Endleſs work to recite all the Examples of this kind that are found in our Hiſtories and Records; but that of <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudley</hi> muſt not be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: They had craftily contrived to aboliſh Grand Juries and to draw the Lives and Eſtates of the People into queſtion, without Indictments by them; and by ſurpriſe, and other wicked pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, they gained an Act of Parliament for their countenance: Hereupon falſe Accuſations followed without number; Oppreſſion and Injuſtice broke forth like a Flood, And to gain the Kings Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor, they filled his Coffers: The Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt them mentioned in <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon</hi>'s Reports, Pa. 156. 157. are worth reading; whereby they are char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>with Treaſon, for Subverting the Laws, and Cuſtoms of the Land, in their proceedings without Grand Juries, and procuring the murmuring &amp; hatred of the People againſt the King, to the great danger of him, &amp; the Kingdom.</hi> Nothing could ſatisfy the Kingdom, tho the King was dead, whom they had flattered, and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:100111:56"/>ſerved, but ſuch Juſtice done upon them, and many of their Inſtruments, and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, as may for ever make the Ears of Judges to tingle.</p>
            <p>And it is not to be forgotten, that the Judges in Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> time, in the Caſe of R. <hi>Cavendiſh</hi> in <hi>Anderſon</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports P. 152, and 155. <hi>were</hi> (as they told the Queen, and her Councellors) <hi>by the puniſhment of former Judges, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially of</hi> Empſon <hi>and</hi> Dudley, <hi>deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from obeying her illegal Commands:</hi> The Queen had ſent ſeveral Letters un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her Signet; Great Men preſſed them to obey her Patent under the Great Seal, and the Reaſons of their diſobedience being required; They anſwered, <hi>That the Queen her ſelf, and the Judges, alſo had taken an Oath to keep the Laws; And if they ſhould obey her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, the Laws would not warrant them, and they ſhould therein break their Oath, to the Offence of God, and their Country, and the Common-wealth where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they were born; And,</hi> ſay they, <hi>if we had no fear of God, yet the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:100111:56"/>and puniſhments of others before us, who did offend the Laws, do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, and recal us from the like Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whoſoever being in the like places may deſign, or be put upon the like practices, will do well to conſider theſe Examples, and not to think, that he, who obliquely Endeavors to render Grand Jurys uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, is leſs Criminal, than he, that would abſolutely aboliſh them: That which doth not act according to its Inſtitution, is, as if it were not in being: And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever doth without prejudice conſider this matter, will ſee that it is not leſs pernicious to deny Juries the uſe of thoſe Methods of diſcovering Truth which the Law hath appointed, and ſo by degrees turn them into a meer mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of form, than openly, and avowedly to deſtroy them. Surely ſuch a gradual Method of deſtroying our Native Right is the moſt dangerous in its conſequence. The ſafety, which our Fore-fathers for many hundreds of years, enjoyed under this part of the Law eſpecially,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:100111:57"/>and have tranſmitted to us, is ſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to the meaneſt Capacity, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall go about to take it away, or give it up, is like to meet with the fate of <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> to have every mans hand againſt him, becauſe his is againſt every Man. Artifices of this Kind, will ruine us more ſilently, and ſo with leſs op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and yet as certainly, as the other more moved oppreſſion: This only is the difference, that one way we ſhould be ſlaves immediately, and the other inſenſibly; But with this further diſadvantage too, that our ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſhould be the more unavoydable, and the faſter rivited upon us, becauſe it would be under colour of Law, which Practice in Time would obtain.</p>
            <p>Few men at firſt ſee the danger of little changes in Fundamentals, and thoſe, who deſign them, uſually act with ſo much craft, as beſides the giving ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Reaſons, they take great Care, that the true Reaſon ſhall not appear: Every deſign therefore of changing the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution ought to be moſt warily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:100111:57"/>and timely oppoſed; Nor is it only the Intereſt of the People, that ſuch Fundamentals ſhould be duly guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for whoſe benefit they were at firſt ſo carefully layed, and whom the Judges are ſworn to ſerve; but of the King too, for whoſe ſake thoſe pretend to act, who would ſubvert them.</p>
            <p>Our Kings as well as Judges are ſworn to maintain the Laws; They have them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſeveral Statutes required the Judges, at their peril, to adminiſter E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Juſtice to every Man, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Letters, or Commands, &amp;c. even from themſelves to the contrary; And when any failure hath been, the greateſt, and moſt powerful of them have ever been the readieſt to give Redreſs. It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the preface to the Statutes of 20th <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. that the Judicial proceedings had been perverted, That Letters writs and Commands had been ſent from the King, and great Men to the Juſtices, and that Perſons belonging to the Court of the King, the Queen, the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> had maintained, &amp; abetted Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:100111:58"/>&amp;c. Whereby the Laws had been violated, and many wrongs done: But the King was ſo far from juſtifying his own Letters, or thoſe illegal practices: That the preamble of thoſe Statutes ſaith, they were made for the relief of the People in their ſufferings by them. That brave King in the height of his glory, and vigor of his Age, choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to confeſs his Error, than to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in it, as is Evident by his own words. Edward <hi>by the Grace of God, &amp;c. Becauſe by divers Complaints made unto us, we have perceived that the Law of the Land, which we by our Oath are bound to maintain, is the leſs well kept, and Execution of the ſame diſturbed many times by maintenances and procurements; as well in the Court, as the Country, We greatly moved of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in this matter, and for this Cauſe, deſiring as much for the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God, and eaſe and quietneſs of our Subjects, as to ſave our Conſcience, and for to ſave and keep our ſaid Oath, by the Aſſent,</hi> &amp;c. Enact, <hi>That Judges
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:100111:58"/>ſhall do Juſtice, notwithſtanding Writs, Letters or Commands from himſelf,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and that none of the King's Houſe, or belonging to the King. Queen, or Prince of wales do maintain Quarrells,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> in his Speech to the Judges in the <hi>Starchamber Anno.</hi> 1616. told them; <hi>That He had after many years reſolved to renew his Oath, made at his Coronation, concerning Juſtice and the promiſe therein contained for maintaining the Law of the Land.</hi> And in the next Page ſave one ſays, <hi>I was ſworn to maintain the Law of the Land, and therefore had been perjured, if I had broken it; God is my Judge I never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended it.</hi> And His Majeſty, that now is, hath made frequent Declarations, and Proteſtations of his being far from all thoughts of deſigning an Arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and that the Nation might be confident, He would rule by Law.</p>
            <p>Now if after all this, any Officer of the Kings ſhould pretend Inſtructions from his Maſter, to demand ſo material an Alteration of proceedings, in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:100111:59"/>Caſes againſt Law, as are above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, And the Court (who are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſlight and reject the moſt ſolemn Commands under the Great Seal, if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Law) ſhould upon a Verbal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation allow of ſuch a Demand, and ſo break in upon this Bulwark of out Liberties, which the Law has erected; Might it not give too juſt an occaſion to ſuſpect, that all the legal ſecurities of our Lives, and Properties are unable to protect us? And may not ſuch fears rob the King of his greateſt Treaſure, and Strength, the Peoples hearts, when they dare not rely upon Him in His Kingly Office, and truſt, for ſafety and Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the Laws? Our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hiſtory affords many Inſtances of thoſe that have pretended to ſerve our King in this manner, by undermining the Peoples Right, and Liberties, whoſe practices have ſometimes proved of fatal conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to the Kings themſelves, but more frequently ended in their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>But after all imagining it could be
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:100111:59"/>made out, that this Method of private Examinations by a Grand Jury (which from what has been ſaid before, hath appeared to be ſo Extremely neceſſary for the publick good, and to every pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate mans ſecurity) were inconvenient, or Miſchievous, and therefore fit to be changed; Yet being ſo Eſſential a part of the Common Law, it is no otherwiſe alterable, than by Parliament. We find by Preſidents, that the bare forms of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictments could not be reformed by the Judges: The words <hi>Depopulatores agro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Inſidiatores viarum, Viet Armis, Baculis, Cultellis, Arcubus &amp; ſagittis,</hi> could not be left out, but by Advice of the Kingdom in Parliament. A writ iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Time of K. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. giving Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to hear and determine Offences, and all the Juſtices reſolved (<hi>Cok.</hi> 4. Inſt. Pag. 164.) <hi>That they could not lawfully act, having their Authority by Writ, where they ought to have had it by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; Tho it was in the form and words, that the Legal Commiſſion ought to be.</hi> John Knivett <hi>Chief Juſtice by Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:100111:60"/>of all the Judges reſolved that the ſaid Writ was</hi> Contra Legem: <hi>And where divers Indictments were before them found againſt</hi> T. S. <hi>the ſame, &amp; all, that was done by colour of that Writ, was Damned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If in ſuch ſeeming little Things as theſe, and many others, that may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced, the Wiſdom of the Nation hath not thought fit to intruſt the Judges, but reſerved the Conſideration of them to the Legiſlative Power; It cannot be imagined, that they ſhould ſubject to the diſcretion, and pleaſure of the Judges, thoſe important Points, in the Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed courſe of the adminiſtring Juſtice, whereupon depends the ſafety of all the Subjects Lives, and fortunes. If Judges will take upon themſelves to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the conſtant practice, they muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alter the Oath of the Grand Jury, or continue it; If they ſhould alter it, ſo as to make it ſail with any ſuch new Method, and thus in appearance cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably provide, that the Grand Jury ſhould not take a mock Oath, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwear
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:100111:60"/>themſelves; they then make an Incroachment upon the Authority of Parliaments, who only can make new, or change old Legal Oaths, and all the proceedings thereupon would be void.</p>
            <p>If they ſhould continue conſtantly to impoſe the ſame Oath, as well when they have notice from the King, that the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhall not be bound to keep his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, and their own, as when they have none; They muſt aſſume to make the ſame form of Law to be of force, and no force; and the ſame words to bind the Conſcience, as they will have them; Whereby they would prophane the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Religion of an Oath, and bring a foul Scandal upon Chriſtianity, by trifling worſe than Heathens in that ſacred matter; And whilſt the Judges find themſelves under the neceſſity of adminiſtring the Oath unto Grand Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and not ſuffer them to obſerve it according unto their conſciences, they would confeſs, the illegality of their own Proceedings, and can never be able to repair the Breaches, by pretending a
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:100111:61"/>tacite Implication, if the King will, but muſt unavoidably fall under that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Maxim of our Law, <hi>Maledicta eſt Interpretatio quae corrumpit Tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;</hi> It is a Curſed Interpretation that diſſolves the Text.</p>
            <p>There are Two Vulgar Errours con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the duty of Grand Juries, which if not removed will in Time deſtroy all the benefit we can expect from that Conſtitution, by turning them into a meer matter of form, which were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for ſo great Ends. Many have of late, thought, and affirmed it for Law, that the Grand Jury is neither to make ſo ſtrict Inquiry into matters before them Nor to look for ſo clear Evidence of the Crime, as the Petit Jury; but that of their Preſentments, being to paſs a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Examination, they ought to indict upon a Superficial Inquiry, and bare Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilities: Whereas ſhould either of theſe Opinions be admitted, the Prejudice to the ſubject would be equal to the total laying aſide Grand Juries; There being in Truth no difference, between arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:100111:61"/>without any Preſentment from them at all, and their Preſenting upon ſlight grounds.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, that Grand Juries ought not to make ſo Strict Inquiry, it were to be wiſht, that we might know how it comes to paſs, that an Oath ſhould be obligatory unto a Petit Jury, and not unto the Grand: Or in what Points, they may lawfully, and with good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience omit that Exactneſs, whether in Relation to the Witneſſes, and their credibility: Or the fact and all its cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances: Or the Teſtimony and its weight: Or laſtly, in Reference to the Priſoner, and Probability of his guilt: And withal upon what grounds of Law, or Reaſon their Opinion is founded. On the contrary he that will conſider either the Oath they take, or the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, where their duty is deſcribed, will find in all Points, that there lies an Equal obligation upon them, and the Petit Juries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They ſwear diligently to inquire, and true Preſentment make, &amp;c. and to Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:100111:62"/>the Truth, the whole Truth, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the Truth, &amp;c.</hi> And in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of <hi>Oyer</hi> &amp; <hi>Terminer</hi> their duty (with that of the Commiſſioners) is thus deſcribed: <hi>Ad Inquirendum per Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum Proborum &amp; legalium ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum, &amp;c. per quos rei veritas melius ſciri poterit, de quibuſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> proditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, &amp;c. confoederationibus, Falſis al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legantiis, nec non Acceſſoriis Eorundem, &amp;c. per quoſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp; qualitercun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> habit. fact. perpetrat. ſive Commiſſ. Et per quos, Et per quem, cui, vel quibus quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, qualiter, vel quomodo, &amp; de aliis ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulis &amp; Circumſtantiis praemiſ. &amp; eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum aliquod, vel aliqua qualitercun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> concernen. To inquire by the Oath of honeſt and lawful Men, &amp;c. By whom the Truth of the matter may be beſt known, of all manner of Treaſons &amp;c. Confederacies, falſe Teſtimonies,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>As alſo the Acceſſories,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>by whomſoever, or howſoever, done, perpetrated, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, by whom, or to whom, how, in what way, or in what manner. And of other Articles and Circumſtances pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:100111:62"/>and of any other Thing or Things howſoever concerning the ſame:</hi> Now for any Man, after this to maintain, that Grand Juries are not to inquire, or not carefully, is as much as in plain terms to ſay they are bound to act contrary to the Commiſſion, and their Oath; And to affirm that they can diſcharge their duty according to the obligations of Law and Conſcience, which they lie under, without a ſtrict Inquiry into Particulars, is to affirm, that the End can be obtained without the means ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary unto it.</p>
            <p>The Truth is, that Grand Juries have both a larger field for their Inquiry, and are in many reſpects better capacitated to make a ſtrict one, than the Petit Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: Theſe laſt are confined as to the Perſon and the Crime, ſpecified in the Indictment; But They are at large ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to ſearch into the whole matter, that any ways concerns every caſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and all the Offences contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it, all the Criminal Circumſtances whatſoever, and into every Thing, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:100111:63"/>concerning the ſame. They are bound to inquire whether their Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Suſpected Treaſons or Felonies, brought by Accuſers, be made by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, or Subornation; Who are the Conſpirators, or falſe Witneſſes: By whom abetted, or maintained; Againſt whom, and how many, the Conſpiracy is layed; When, and how, and in what courſe, it was to have been proſecuted.</p>
            <p>But none of theſe moſt intricate mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (which need the moſt ſtrict and diligent Inquiries) can come under the Cogniſance of the Petit Jury; They can only examine ſo much, as relates to the Credit of thoſe Witneſſes brought to prove the Charge againſt the Parties, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted; Wherein alſo they have neither Power, nor convenient time to ſend for perſons, or Papers, if they think them needful, Nor to reſolve any doubts of the Lawfulneſs, and Credibility of the Teſtimonies.</p>
            <p>Yet further, if the Crimes objected are manifeſt, 'tis then the Grand Juries duty to inquire after all the Perſons any
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:100111:63"/>ways concerned in them, and the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Kinds of Offences, whereof every one ought joyntly, or ſeparately to be indicted as they ſhall diſcover them to have been Principals, or Acceſſories Parties or privy thereunto, or to have comforted, or Knowingly relieved either the Traitors or Felons, or conceal'd the offences of others: But the Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into all theſe matters, which require all poſſible ſtrictneſs in ſearching, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the higheſt importance unto the publick Juſtice, and ſafety, is wholly out of the Power &amp; Truſt of the Petit Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. The guilt, or Innocence of the Parties put upon their Tryals, &amp; the Evidence thereof given is the only Objects of their Inquiries. It is not their work, nor within their truſt to ſearch into all the guilt, or Crimes of the Parties, whom they try; They are bound to move within the Circle of the Indictment made by the Grand Jury, who are to appoint, and ſpecify the offences, for which the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed ſhall be tried by the Petit Jury.</p>
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:100111:64"/>
            <p> When a Proſecutor ſuggeſts that any Man is criminal, and ought to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted, it belongs to the Grand Jury to hear all the proof he can offer, &amp; to uſe all other means they can, whereby they may come to underſtand the Truth of the ſuggeſtion &amp; every thing or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, that may concern it; Then they are carefully to examine the nature of the Facts, according unto the Rules of the Com. Law, or the expreſs words of the Statutes, whereby offences are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, and puniſhments allotted unto each of them: Tis true, that upon heat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Party, or his Witneſſes, the Petit Jury may acquit or judge the Facts in the Indictment to be leſs heinous, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious, then they were preſented by the Grand Jury, but cannot aggravate them; which being conſidered, it will Eaſily appear by the intent and Nature of the Powers given unto Grand Juries, that they are by their Oaths obliged, and their inſtitution ordained to keep all injuſtice from entring the firſt gates of our Courts of Judicature, and to ſecure
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:100111:64"/>the innocent not only from puniſhment, but from all diſgrace, vexation, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence or danger.</p>
            <p>To underſtand our Law clearly here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the Jurors muſt firſt know the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful grounds whereupon they may and ought to indict, and then what truly and juſtly ought to be taken for the ground of an Indictment. The princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal and moſt certain is the Jurors perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal knowledge, by their own Eyes or Ears, of the Crimes whereof they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict: Or ſo many pregnant concurring Circumſtances, as fully convince them of the guilt of the Accuſed: When theſe are wanting the Depoſitions of Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and their Authority are their beſt guides in finding Indictments. When ſuch Teſtimonies make the charge ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt and clear to the Jury, they are called Evidence, becauſe they make the guilt of the Criminal evident, and are like the Light that diſcovers what was not ſeen before: All Witneſſes for that reaſon are uſually called the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, taking their name from what
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:100111:65"/>they ought to be: Yet Witneſſes may ſwear directly and poſitively to an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, and be no Evidence of its truth to the Jury; ſometimes ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks may be made upon the Witneſſes, as well in relation to their Reputation and Lives, as to the Matter, Manner, and Circumſtance of their Depoſitions, that from thence the falſhood may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, or be ſtrongly ſuſpected: It is therefore neceſſary to know what they mean by a probable Cauſe or Evidence, who ſay that our Law requires no more for an Indictment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Probable,</hi> is a Logical Term, relating to ſuch propoſitions, as have an appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, but no certainty of Truth, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather what is not, than what is the matter of Syllogiſms: Theſe may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in Rhetorick, which worketh upon paſſions, and makes uſe of ſuch Colors as are fit to move them, whether true or falſe; but not in Logick, whoſe Object is Truth; as it principally intends to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate the Errours that may ariſe from the credit given unto appearances, by
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:100111:65"/>diſtinguiſhing the uncertain from the certain, <hi>veriſimile à vero,</hi> it cannot admit of ſuch Propoſitions, as may be falſe as well as true, it being as impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to draw a certain concluſion from uncertain premiſes, as to raiſe a ſolid Building upon a tottering or ſinking Foundation. This ought principally to be conſidered in Courts of Juſtice, which are not erected to bring men into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, but to find who deſerves to be condemned, and thoſe Rules are to be followed by them, which are leaſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to deception. For this Reaſon the Council of the <hi>Areopagites,</hi> and ſome others of the beſt Judicatures that have been in the World, utterly rejected the uſe of Rhetorick, looking upon the Art of perſuading by uncertain proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, as little differing from that of deceiving, &amp; directly contrary to their ends, who by the knowledge of truth deſired to be led into the doing of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: But if the Art that made uſe of their probabilities was baniſht from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupted Tribunals, as a hindrance un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:100111:66"/>the diſcovery of Truth, they that would ground Verdicts totally upon them, declare an open neglect of it; and as it is ſaid, that <hi>uno abſurdo dato mille ſequuntur,</hi> if Juries were to be guided by probabilities, the next que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion would be concerning the more or leſs probable, or what degree of proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility is required to perſuade them to find a Bill: This being impoſſible to fix, the whole Proceedings would be brought to depend upon the Fancies of Men, and as nothing is ſo ſlight but it may move them, there is no ſecurity that innocent Perſons may not be brought every day into danger and trouble. By this means certain miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs will be done, whilſt it is by their own confeſſion uncertain, whether they are any ways deſerved by ſuch as ſuffer them, to the utter overthrow of all Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
            <p>If the word <hi>Probable</hi> be taken in a common, rather than a nice Logical ſenſe, it ſignifies no more than likely, or rather likely than unlikely: When a
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:100111:66"/>matter is found to be ſo, the Wager is not even, there is odds upon one ſide, and this may be a very good ground, for betting in a Tennis Court, or at a Horſe race, but he that would make the Adminiſtration of Juſtice to depend upon ſuch Points, ſeems to put a very ſmall value upon the Fortunes, liberties and reputation of men, and to forget that thoſe who ſet in Courts of Juſtice have no other buſineſs there than to preſerve them.</p>
            <p>This continues in force, tho in a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue between a Barriſter, and a Grand Jury man, publiſhed under the Title of the Grand Jury Mans Oath and Office, it be ſaid p. 8. and 9. <hi>That their work is no more than to preſent Offences fit for a Tryal, and for that Reaſon, give in only a Veriſimilar or probable charge; and others have affirmed, that a far leſs Evidence will warrant a Grand Juries Indictment, than a petit Juries Verdict.</hi> For Nothing can be more oppoſite to the Juſtice of our Laws, than ſuch Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions: All Laws in doubtful Caſes direct
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:100111:67"/>a ſuſpenſion of Judgment, or a ſentence in favour of the Accuſed, perſon: But if this were hearkened unto, Grand Juries ſhould upon their Oaths affirm, they judge him Criminal, when the Evidence is upon ſuch uncertain grounds that they cannot but doubt, whether he is ſo or not.</p>
            <p>It cannot be hereupon ſaid, that no Evidence is ſo clear and full, but it may be falſe, and give the Jury occaſion of doubts, ſo as all Criminals muſt eſcape, if no Indictment ought to be found un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the proofs are abſolutely certain, for it is confeſſed, that ſuch Caſes are not capable of an infallible, Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal demonſtration; but a Jury, that Examines all the Witneſſes, that are likely to give any Light concerning the buſineſs in queſtion, and all Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces relating to the fact before them, with the Lives and Credit of thoſe that teſtify it, and of the Perſon accuſed, may and do often find that which in their Conſciences, doth fully perſwade them, that the accuſed Perſon is guilty; This
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:100111:67"/>is as much as the Law, or their Oath doth require, and ſuch as find bills, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having made ſuch a Scrutiny, are blamleſs before God, and Man, if through the fragility inſeparable from humane nature, they ſhould be led into Error? For they do not ſwear, that the bill is true, but that they in their Conſciences believe that it is ſo; And if they write <hi>Ignoramus</hi> upon the Bill, it is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by declared to be falſe, nor the Perſon accuſed acquitted, but the matter is ſuſpended, until it can be more clearly proved, as in doubtful Caſes, it alwaies ought to be.</p>
            <p>Our Anceſtors took great Care that ſuſpicious, and probable Cauſes ſhould not bring any Mans Life, and Eſtate into danger; For that reaſon, it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by the Stat. 37. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. Cap. 18. <hi>That ſuch as made ſuggeſtions to the King; ſhould find ſurety to purſue and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur the ſame pain, that the other ſhould have had if he were attainted, in caſe their ſuggeſtion be found evil &amp; that then proceſs of the Law ſhould be made againſt the Accuſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="132" facs="tcp:100111:68"/>
            <p> This manner of Proceeding, hath its root on eternal, and univerſal Reaſon: The Law given by God unto his People, <hi>Deut.</hi> 19. allotted the ſame Puniſhment unto a falſe witneſs, as a Perſon convict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The beſt diſciplined Nations of the world, learnt this from the Hebrews, and made it their Rule, in the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Juſtice. The Grecians gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally obſerved it, and the <hi>Romans,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their <hi>Lex Talionis,</hi> did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſh death with death, but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of committing Murther by falſe Accuſations, with the ſame ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as if it had been effected by any other means. This Law was inviolably obſerved as long as any thing of regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity or equity remained amongſt them; and when through the wickedneſs of ſome of the Emperours, or their favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, it came to be overthrown, all Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice periſhed with it. A Crew of falſe Informers brake out to the deſtruction of the beſt men, and never ceaſed until they had ruined all the moſt eminent and antient Families: Circumvented
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:100111:68"/>the Perſons, that by their Reputation, Wealth, Birth or Virtue deſerved to be diſtinguiſhed from the common ſort of People, and brought deſolation, upon that victorious City.<note place="margin">Tac. Ann. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tacitus</hi> complains of this, as the cauſe of all the miſchiefs ſuffered in his Time, and Country.</p>
            <p>By their means the moſt Savage Cruelties, were committed under the name of Law, which thereby became a greater Plague, than formerly crimes had been: No remedy could be found, when thoſe <hi>Delatores,</hi> whom he calls, <hi>genus hominum Publico exitio repertum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tac. Ann. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; poenis quidem nunquam ſatis coercitum,</hi> were invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by impunity, or reward, and the Miſerable People groaned under this calamity, until thoſe inſtruments of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, were by better Princes, put to the moſt cruel, though well deſerved deaths.</p>
            <p>The like hath been ſeen in many Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the domeſtick quiet, which is now enjoyed in the Principal parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> proceeds chiefly from this,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:100111:69"/>that every man knows the ſame Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, is appointed for a falſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, and a proved crime.</p>
            <p>It is hardly ſeven years ſince Monſieur <hi>Courboyer,</hi> a man of quality in <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany,</hi> ſuborned two of the King of <hi>France</hi> his Guards, to ſwear Treaſonable Deſigns againſt <hi>La Motte,</hi> a <hi>Norman</hi> Gentleman; The matter being brought to Monſieur <hi>Colebert,</hi> he cauſed the Accuſed Perſon and the witneſſes to be ſecured, until the fraud was diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by one of them, whereupon he was pardoned? <hi>La Motte</hi> releaſed: <hi>Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyer</hi> beheaded, and the other falſe Witneſs hanged by the Sentence of the Parliament of <hi>Paris.</hi> Though this Law ſeems to be grounded upon ſuch foundation, as forbids us to queſtion the equity of it, our Anceſtors (for Reaſons beſt known unto themſelves) thought fit to moderate its Severity, by the Statute of 38. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 9. yet then it was enacted, and the Law continues in force unto this day; <hi>That whoſoever made complaints to the King, and could
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:100111:69"/>not prove them againſt the defendant,</hi> by the proceſs of Law limited in former Statutes, which is firſt by a Grand Jury, he <hi>ſhould be impriſoned until he had made gree to the Party of his damages, and of the ſlander he ſuffered by ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and after ſhall make fine and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom to the King,</hi> which is for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon damage, that the King and his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſuffer by ſuch a falſe accuſation and defamation of any Subject: And in the 42. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap</hi> 3. <hi>To eſchew the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs and damage done by falſe Accuſers</hi> 'Tis enacted, that <hi>no man be put to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> ſuch ſuggeſtions <hi>without preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before the Juſtices, i. e.</hi> by the Grand Jury: It cannot ſurely be imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the ſuggeſtions made to the King and his Council, had no probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in them, Or that there was no co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, cauſe, or Reaſon for the King to put the party to anſwer the Accuſation, but the grievance and complaint was, that the People ſuffered certain damage, and vexation upon untrue, and at beſt, uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain accuſations, and that therein the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:100111:70"/>Law was perverted by the King and his Councils taking upon them, to judge of the certainty, or Truth of them, which of right belonged to the Grand Jury on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, upon whoſe Judgment and Integrity our Law doth wholly rely, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity of the Innocent, and the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of all ſuch as do unjuſtly moleſt them.</p>
            <p>Our Laws have not thought fit ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely to depend upon the Oaths of Witneſſes, as to allow, that upon Two, or Ten mens ſwearing poſitively Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Felony againſt any Man, before the Juſtices of peace, or all the Judges, or before the King and his Council, that the party accuſed, be he either Peer of the Realm or Commoner, ſhould with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further Inquiry be thereupon ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rained, and put upon his Tryal for his Life: Yet none can doubt but there is ſomething of probability in ſuch depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions nevertheleſs the Law Refers thoſe matters unto Grand Juries, and no man can be brought to Tryal, until upon ſuch ſtrict Inquiries, (as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:100111:70"/>ſaid) the Indictment be found. The Law is ſo ſtrict in theſe Inquiries, that tho the Crime be never ſo notorious, may if Treaſon ſhould be confeſſed in Writing under hand and ſeal, before Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of Peace, Secretaries of State, or the King and Council, yet before the party can be arrained for it, the Grand Jury muſt inquire, and be ſatisfied, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch a Confeſſion be clear and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain: Whether there was no colluſion therein: Or the party induced to ſuch confeſſion by promiſe of pardon: Or that ſome pretended partakers in the Crime may be defamed, or deſtroyed thereby; They muſt inquire, whether the Confeſſion was not extorted by fear, threatnings, or force, and whether the party was truly <hi>Compos mentis,</hi> of ſound mind, and Reaſon at that Time.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Stat.</hi> 5. <hi>Eliz.</hi> Cap. 1. declares the antient Common Law concerning the Truſt and duty of Juries, and Enacts that none ſhould <hi>be indicted for aſſiſting, aiding, comforting, or abelting</hi> Criminals in the Treaſons therein made and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:100111:71"/>
               <hi>unleſs he, or they be thereof law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully accuſed by ſuch good and ſufficient Teſtimony or proof, as by the Jury, by whom he ſhall be indicted, ſhall be thought good, lawful, and ſufficient to prove him, or them guilty of the Said Offences.</hi> Herein is declared, the only True Reaſon of Indictments, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Grand Juries Judgment that they have ſuch Teſtimonies as they eſteem ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to prove the party indicted guilty of the Crimes whereof he is accuſed, and whatſoever the Indictment doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, they are to preſent no more, or other Crimes, than are proved to their ſatisfaction, as upon Oath they declare it is, when they preſent it. This exactneſs is not only required in the Subſtance of Crimes, but in the Circumſtances, and any doubtfulneſs, or uncertainty in them makes the Indictment, &amp; all proceedings upon it by the Petit Jury, to be inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and void, and holden for none, as appears by the following Caſes.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Youngs</hi> Caſe in the Lord <hi>Cooks</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Fol.</hi> 40. An Indictment for
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:100111:71"/>Murther was declared void for its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty, becauſe the Jury had not lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed certainty, in what part of the body the mortal wound was given, ſaying on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that 'twas about his breaſt, the words were <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nam Plagam mortalem circiter pectus.</hi> In like manner in <hi>Vaux</hi> Caſe <hi>Cooks</hi> Rep. <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Fol.</hi> 44. he being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted for poiſoning <hi>Ridley,</hi> the Jury had not plainly and expreſly averred that <hi>Ridley</hi> drank the Poiſon, tho other words implyed it, and thereupon the Indictment was judged inſufficient <hi>for</hi> (ſaith the book) <hi>the matter of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment ought to be full, expreſs, and certain, and ſhall not be maintained by argument or implication, for that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment is found by the Oath of the Neighborhood.</hi> In the 2d part of <hi>Rolls</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports <hi>p.</hi> 263. <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Malls</hi> Caſe the Indictment was quaſhed for incertainty, becauſe the Jury had averred that <hi>Smith</hi> was either a ſervant or Deputy, <hi>Smith Exiſtens ſervus ſive Deputatus,</hi> are the words: It was doubtleſs probably enough proven to the Jury, that he was
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:100111:72"/>Either a Deputy, or ſervant, but becauſe the Indictment did not abſolutely and certainly aver his condition Either of ſervant, or Deputy, it was declared void: If there be any defect of certainty in the Grand Juries Verdict, no proof or Evidence to the Petit Jury can ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it, ſo it was judged in <hi>Wrote</hi> and <hi>Wigs</hi> Caſe <hi>Coke</hi> 4. Rep. <hi>Fol.</hi> 45, 46, 47. It was layed, that <hi>Wrote</hi> was killed at <hi>Shipperton,</hi> but did not aver that <hi>Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perton</hi> was within the <hi>Verge,</hi> tho in truth it was, and no Averment or Oath to the Petit Jury, could ſupply that ſmall faileur of certainty to ſupport the Indictment; and the reaſon is rendred in theſe words, <hi>viz. The Indictment being Veredictum id eſt dictum Veritatis a Verdict, That is, a ſaying of Truth and matter of Record, ought to contain the whole Truth which is requiſite by the Law, for when it doth not appear, 'tis the ſame, as if it were not, and every material part of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment ought to be found upon the Oath if the Indicters and cannot be ſupplied by the Averment of the Party.</hi> The
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:100111:72"/>Grand Juries Verdict is the foundation of all judicial proceeding againſt Capital Offenders (at the King ſuit) if that fail in any point of certainty, both convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and acquittals thereupon, are ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly void, and the proceedings againſt both may begin agen, as if they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been tried, as it appears in the Caſe laſt cited, <hi>Fol.</hi> 47.</p>
            <p>Now as the Law requires from the Grand Jury Particular, certain and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe affirmations of Truth, ſo it expects that they ſhould look for the like, and accept of no other from ſuch as bring accuſations to them. For no man can cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly affirm that which is uncertainly delivered unto him, or which he doth not firmly believe. The witneſſes that they receive for good, are to depoſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abſolute certaintys about the Facts committed, That is, what they have ſeen, or heard from the accuſed parties themſelves, not what others have told them; They are not to be ſuffered to make probable arguments, and infer from thence the guilt of the accuſed; Their
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:100111:73"/>depoſitions ought to be poſitive, plain, direct and full: The Crime is to be ſworn without any doubtfulneſs, or obſcurity; Not in words qualified, &amp; limited to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, conceptions, or apprehenſions. This abſolute certainty required in the depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Witneſſes, is one principal ground of the Juries moſt rational aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of the Truth of their Verdict: The credit alſo of the Witneſſes ought to be free from all blemiſh, that good, and Conſcientious men may rationally rely upon them, in matters of ſo great moment, as the bloud of a man. It muſt alſo be certainly evident, that all the matters which they depoſe, are conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with each other and accompanied with ſuch circumſtances, as in their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment render it credible: All juſt Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, muſt be built upon theſe moral aſſurances, which the wiſdom of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions hath deviſed as the beſt, and only way of deciding Controverſies; Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can a Grand Jury man, who ſwears to preſent nothing but the Truth, be ſatisfied with leſs.</p>
            <pb n="143" facs="tcp:100111:73"/>
            <p>'Tis ſcarce credible that any learned in our Laws, ſhould tell a Grand Jury that a far leſs Evidence will warrant their Indictment (being but an Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) than the Petit Jury ought to have, for their Verdict. Both of them do in like manner, plainly, and poſitively affirm upon their Oaths, the Truth of the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation; Their Verdicts are indeed one, and the ſame in ſubſtance, and ſenſe, tho not in words. There is no real dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, between affirming in Writing, that an Indictment of Treaſon is true, as is the practice of Grand Juries, and ſaying that the party tried thereupon is guilty of the Treaſon, whereof he is indicted, as is the courſe of Petit Juries: They are both upon their Oaths; They are equally obligatory into both; The one therefore muſt expect the ſame proof for their ſatisfaction, as the other, and as clear Evidence muſt be required for an Indictment, as for a Verdict; It is unreaſonable to think that a ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter proof, ſhould ſatisfie the Conſciences of the greater Jury, than is requiſite to
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:100111:74"/>convince the leſs; And uncharitable to imagin, that thoſe ſhould not be as ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible as the others of the Sacred ſecurity they have given by Oath, to do nothing in their Offices, but according to truth.</p>
            <p>If there ought to be any difference in the Proceedings of the Grand and Petit Juries, the greater exactneſs and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence ſeems to be required in the Grand: For as the ſame work of finding out the truth in order to the doing of Juſtice is allotted unto both, the greateſt part of the burthen, ought to lye upon them, that have the beſt opportunities of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming it. The invalidity weakneſs, or defects of the Proofs may be Equally Evident to either of them: But if there be deceit in ſtifling true Teſtimonies, or malice in ſuborning wicked Perſons, to bring in ſuch as are falſe, the Grand Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry may moſt eaſily, nay probably, can only diſcover it. They are not ſtraitned in time; They may freely examine in private, without interruption from the Council, or Court, ſuch Witneſſes, as are preſented unto them, or they
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:100111:74"/>ſhall think fit to call; they may jointly or ſeverally enquire of their Friends or Acquaintance, after the Lives and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations of the Witneſſes, or the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed Perſons, and all circumſtances re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating unto the matter in queſtion, and conſult together under the Seal of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy: On the other ſide the Petty Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry being charged with the Priſoner, acts in open Court, under the Awe of the Judges: is Subject to be diſturb'd, or interrupted by Council: Deprived of all opportunity of Conſulting one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, until the Evidence be ſumm'd up, and not ſuffered to eat or drink, until they bring in a Verdict; ſo is it almoſt impoſſible for them thus limited to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover ſuch evil practices, as may be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for, or againſt the Priſoner, by Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ornation or Perjury to pervert Juſtice; if therefore the Grand Jury be not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to perform this part of their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, it is hard to imagine how it ſhould be done at all: And it is much more inconceivable how they can ſatisfie their Conſciences, if they ſo neglect, as
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:100111:75"/>to find a Bill upon an imperfect Evidence, in the abſence of the Priſoner in Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation that it will be ſupplied at the Bar: It concerns them therefore to remember, that if they proceed upon ſuch uncertainties, they will certainly give incurable Wounds into their Neighbours Reputations, in order unto the deſtruction of their Perſons.</p>
            <p>Whatever ground this Doctrine of Indicting upon ſlight proofs may have got in our days, it is (as we have ſeen) both againſt Law and Reaſon, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the practice of former times. My Lord <hi>Coke</hi> in his <hi>Comment</hi> on <hi>Weſtm.</hi> 2d. tells us, <hi>That in thoſe days (and as yet it ought to be) Indictments taken in the Abſence of the Party were form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon plain and direct Proofs, and not upon Probabilities and Inferences,</hi> Herein we ſee, that the practice of our Fore-Fathers, and the opinion of this great and judicious Lawyer, were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt this new Doctrine, and ſome that have carefully looked back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, obſerved, that there are very
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:100111:75"/>few Examples of men acquitted by Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit Juries, becauſe Grand Juries of old were ſo wary in canvaſing every thing narrowly, and ſo ſenſible of their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in proceeding according unto truth upon Satisfactory Evidence, that few or none were brought unto Trial till their Guilt ſeemed evident.</p>
            <p>It is therefore a great miſtake, to think that the ſecond Juries were inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted for the hearing of fuller proofs; That was not their work, but to give an opportunity to the accuſed perſons to anſwer for themſelves, and make their defence, which cannot be thought to ſtrengthen the Evidence, unleſs they be ſuppoſed to play booty againſt their own Lives. By way of anſwer the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner may avoid the charge: He is permitted to take Exceptions; he may demur or plead to the Indictments in points of Law: Herein the Judges ought to aſſiſt him, and appoint Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel if he deſire it: He may ſhew that the Indictors, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Grand Jury, or ſome of them, are not lawful
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:100111:76"/>men, or not lawfully returned by the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs; embracery or practice may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the packing of the Jury: A Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, or Subornation may be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; Falſhood may be found out in the Witneſſes, by queſtions about ſome circumſtances that none could have asked, or imagined, except the Party accuſed: And beſides doing right to the Indicted, in theſe and many other things, 'tis the Peoples due to have all the Evidence firſt taken in private, to be afterwards made publick at the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, that the Kingdom may be ſatisfied in the equal adminiſtration of Juſtice, and that the Judgments againſt Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals may be of greater Terrour, and more uſeful to preſerve the common peace.</p>
            <p>If any object that this Doctrine would introduce double Trials for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry offence, and all the delays that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company them, it may be anſwered. That <hi>Nulla unquam de morte hominis cunctatio Longa eſt,</hi> Ju. Sat. No delay is to be eſteemed Long, when the life of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:100111:76"/>a man is in queſtion. The puniſhment of an offendor, that is a little deferred, may be compenſated by its ſeverity, but blood raſhly ſpilt, cannot be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up, and a Land polluted by it, is hardly cleanſed. Wiſe, and good men, in matters of this nature, have ever proceeded with extream caution, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt the ſwift of foot are in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture repreſented under an ill Character, and have been often found in their haſte to draw more guilt upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, than what they pretended to chaſtize in others. To avoid this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, in many well poliſhed King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, ſeveral Courts of Juſtice are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, who take cognizance of the ſame facts, but ſo ſubordinate unto one another, that in matters of life, limb, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, or other important caſes, there is a right of appeal from the inferior, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which it is firſt brought, to the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior where this is wanting, means have been found to give opportunity unto the Judges to reflect upon their own ſentences, that if any thing had
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:100111:77"/>been done raſhly, or through miſtake, it might be corrected, man, even in his beſt eſtate, ſeeming to have need of ſome ſuch helps. <hi>Tiberius Caeſar</hi> was never accuſed of too much lenity, but when he heard that <hi>Lutorius 'Priſcus,</hi> had been accuſed of Treaſon before the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, condemned, and immediately put to death, <hi>Tam praecipites deprecatus eſt poenas,</hi> He deſired that ſuch ſudden puniſhment might for the future be forborn, and a Law was thereupon made, <hi>That no Decree of the Senate ſhould in leſs than ten days be tranſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Treaſury,</hi> before which time it could not be executed, <hi>Tac. An.</hi> 3. Matters of this nature concerning eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man in <hi>England,</hi> it is not to be doubted but our Anceſtors conſider'd them, and our conſtitutions, neither ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of ſubordinate Judicatures from whence appeals may be made, nor gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving opportunities unto Juries to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>examine their Verdicts, after they were given, they could not find a way more ſuitable unto the rules of Wiſdom, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:100111:77"/>and Mercy, than to appoint two Juries with equal care, according unto different methods, the one in private, and at leiſure, the other publickly in the preſence of the party, and more ſpeedy to paſs upon every man, ſo as none can be condemned, unleſs he be thought guilty by them both, and it cannot be imagined, that ſo little time, as is uſually ſpent in Trials at the Bar, before a Petit Jury, ſhould be allowed unto one that pleads for his life, or unto them who are to be ſatisfied in their conſciences, unleſs it were preſumed, that the Grand Jury, had ſo well exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, prepared, and diſgeſted the matter, that the other may proceed more ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinctly, without danger of error.</p>
            <p>Therefore let the Grand Juries faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully perfom thei high Truſt, and neither be cheated nor frighted from their Duty: Let them purſue the good old way, ſince no Innovation can be brought in, that will not turn to the prejudice of the accuſed Peſons, and themſelves: Let them not be deluded
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:100111:78"/>with frivolous Arguments, ſo as to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>validate a conſiderable part of our Law, and render themſelves inſignificant ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, in Expectation that Petit Juries will repair the faults they commit, ſince that would be no leſs than to ſlight one of the beſt fences that the Law pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides for our Lives and Liberties, and very much to weaken the other.</p>
            <p>When a Grand Jury finds a Bill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any perſon, they do all that in them lies to take away his Life, if the crime be capital, and it is ridiculous for them to pretend they relie upon the virtue of the Petit Jury, if they ſhew none in themſelves. They cannot rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably hope the other ſhould be more tender of the Priſoners concernments, more exact in doing Juſtice, or more careful in examining the Credit of the Witneſſes, when they have not only neglected their duty of ſearching into it, but added ſtrength unto their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony by finding a Bill upon it.</p>
            <p>They cannot poſſibly be exempted from the blame of conſenting (at the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:100111:78"/>leaſt) unto the miſchiefs that may enſue, unleſs they uſe all the honeſt care that the Law allows to prevent them; nor conſequently avoid the ſtain of the blood that may be ſhed by their omiſſion, ſince it could not have been, if they had well performed their part before they found the Indictment, whereby the Party is expoſed to ſo many diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, that it is hard for the cleareſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence to defend itſelf againſt them.</p>
            <p>But when the one and the other Jury act as they ought, with courage, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and indifference, we ſhall have juſt reaſon, with the wiſe Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour <hi>Forteſcue,</hi> to celebrate that Law that inſtituted them. To congratulate with our Countrey men the happineſs we enjoy, whileſt our Lives lie not <hi>at the mercy of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Witneſſes, hired,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fort. de laud. Leg. Ang. <hi>cap. 26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>poor, uncertain, whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation or malice we are ſtrangers to, but Neighbours of Subſtance, of honeſt report, brought into Court by an honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſworn Officer; men who know the</hi> 
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
            <pb n="156" facs="tcp:100111:79"/>
            <p> POſtquam Rex per ſpatium trium Annorum &amp; amplius in partibus tranſmarinis remanſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet,<note place="margin">Ex Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co ab Anno <hi>1272. 1 Ed. 1.</hi> ad An. <hi>1317.10.</hi> Ed. <hi>2.</hi> Mſſ.</note> &amp; de partibus Vaſconiae &amp; Franciae in Angliam rediiſſet, valde anxiatus &amp; conturbatus fuit per quotidianum clamorem tam Cleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum quam Laicorum petentium ab eo congruum remedium apponi verſus Juſticiarios,<note place="margin">An. Dom. <hi>2289.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Regis <hi>Ed. 1.18.</hi>
               </note> &amp; alios Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtros ſuos, de multimodis op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſionibus &amp; gravaminibus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra bonas leges &amp; conſuetudines regni illis factis;<note place="margin">Certe ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus quam plurimos eorum qui judiciis ſub Ed. <hi>1.</hi> prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuere viros quidem maximos &amp; aevo in illo Juriſ-conſultos celeberri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tundarum &amp; quod li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſuas fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerant ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtros, foren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes aliquot merito dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natos multos exitia &amp; car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere punitos. Ex Seldein ad Fletam diſſertatio. <hi>p. 548.</hi>
               </note> ſuper quo Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus Edvardus Rex, per regale ſcriptum Vicecomitibus Angliae praecipit quod in omnibus Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus, Civitatibus, &amp; Villis mercatoriis, publice proclamari facerent quod omnes qui ſeſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient gravari venirent apud Weſtm. ad proximum Parliamentum, &amp; ibi querimonias ſuas monſtrarent, ubi tam majores quam minores opportunum remedium &amp; cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem juſtitiam recuperent, ſicut Rex
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:100111:80"/>vinculo juramenti die Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronationis ſuae aſtrictus fuit: Ac jam adeſt magnus dies &amp; judiciarius Juſticiorum &amp; aliorum Miniſtrorum Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilii Regis, quem nulla ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giverſatione, nullo mune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, nulla arte vel ingenio placitandi va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent eludi. Coadunatis itaque Clero &amp; Populo &amp; in magno Palatio Weſtmona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterii conſeſſis, Archiepiſcopus Cantu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arienſis (vir magnae pietatis &amp; columna quaſi ſanctae Eccleſiae &amp; Regni) ſurrexit in medio, &amp; ab alto ducens ſuſpiria, Noverit univerſitas veſtra (ait) quod convocati ſumus de magnis &amp; arduis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiis regni (heu nimis perturbati &amp; his diebus enormiter mutilati) unanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miter, fideliter, &amp; efficaciter fimul cum Domino Rege ad tractandum &amp; ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandum, audiviſtis etiam univerſi que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimonias graviſſimas ſuper intolerabilibus injuriis &amp; oppreſſionibus &amp; quotidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis deſolationibus,<note place="margin">Vide Fleta Cap. <hi>17. p. 18, 19.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritas &amp; Officium or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarii Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilii Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis.</note> tam ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae Eccleſ. quam Reg. factis
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:100111:81"/>per hoc iniquum Concili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Domini Regis contra magnas Chartas tot, toties &amp; multoties emptas &amp; redemptas, conceſſas &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatas per tot &amp; ta lia. Juramenta Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini Regis nunc, &amp; Dominorum Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici &amp; Johannis, ac per terribiles ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minationes Excommunicationis ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae in tranſgreſſores communium liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatum Angliae, quae in chartis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictis continentur corroboratas, &amp; cum ſpes praeconcepta de libertatibus illis obſervandis fideliter ab omnibus puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur ſtabilis &amp; indubitata, Rex conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis malorum Miniſtrorum praeventus &amp; ſeductus eaſdem infringendo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travenire non formidavit, credens decep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive pro munere abſolvi à tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne quod eſſet manifeſtum regni exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minium.</p>
            <p>Aliud etiam nos omnes angit intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecus quod Juſticiarii ſubtiliter ex mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ſua ac per diverſa argumenta avari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, &amp; intolerabilis ſuperbiae Regem contra fideles ſuos multipliciter provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caverunt
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:100111:82"/>&amp; incitaverunt, ſanoque &amp; ſalubri conſilio Ligeorum Angliae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarium reddideruut, conſilia ſua vana impudenter praeponere &amp; affirmare non erubuerunt ſeu formidaverunt, ac ſi plus babiles eſſent ad conſulendam &amp; conſervandam Rempublicam quam to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Univerſitas Regni in unum collecta. Ita de illis poſſit vere dici, viri qui tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baverunt terram &amp; concuſſerunt Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſub fuco gravitatis totum popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum graviter oppreſſerunt, praetextu<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſolummodo exponendi vereres Leges, novas (non dicam Leges) ſed malas conſuetudines introduxerunt &amp; vomue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, ita quod per ignorantiam nonnul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum ac per partialitatem aliorum qui vel per munera vel timorem aliquorum potentum innodati fuerunt, nulla fuit ſtabilitas Legum nec alicui de populo Juſtitiam dignabantur exhibere, opera eorum ſunt opera nequitiae, &amp; opus i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquitatis in manibus, pedes eorum ad malum current &amp; feſtinant, ac vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am recti neſcierunt. Quid dicam? non eſt judicium in greſſibus ſuis.<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:100111:83"/>agros &amp; violenter tulerunt &amp; rapuerunt domos &amp; oppreſſerunt virum &amp; domum ejus imo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; Haereditatem ſuam, vae Judices qui ſicut Lupi veſpere non relinquebant oſſa in mane; Juſtus Judex adducit Conſiliarios in ſtultum fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem &amp; Judices in ſtuporem, mox alta voce juſtum Judicium terrae recipietis.</p>
            <p>His auditis omnium aures tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niebant totaque Communitas inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muerunt,<note place="margin">Vide Mat. Weſt. Anno <hi>1289.</hi> p. <hi>376.</hi> li. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> dicentes heu nobis, heu, ubi eſt Angliae toties empta, toties conceſſa, toties ſcripta, toties jurata Libertas?</p>
            <p>Alii de Criminalibus ſeſe à viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus populi ſubtrahentes in locis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretis cum amicis tacite latitave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt,<note place="margin">Anno vero <hi>1290.</hi> (<hi>18.</hi> Ed. <hi>1.</hi>) depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſis omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Angliae Juſticiariis de repetun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis (praeter Jo. Meting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, &amp; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam de Bleckingham quos honor is ergo nominatos volui) judicio Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti vindicatum eſt in alios, atque alios carcere, exilio, fortunarumque omnium diſpendio, in ſingulos mulcta graviſſima &amp; amiſſione officii. <hi>Spelmans Gloſſary, p. 1.</hi> co. <hi>1.416.</hi>
               </note> alios protulerunt in medium unde merito fere omnes ab officiis depoſiti &amp; amoti, unus à terra ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulatus alii perpetuis priſonis incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerati, alii que gravibus pecunia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſolutionibus juſte adjudicati fuerunt.
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:100111:84"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
            <pb n="157" facs="tcp:100111:79"/>
            <p>AFter that the King for the ſpace of three Years and more, had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained beyond Sea, and returned out of <hi>Gaſcoign</hi> and <hi>France</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> he was much vexed and diſturbed by the continual clamour both of the Clergy and Laity, deſiring to be relieved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Juſtices, and other His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſizes Miniſters, of ſeveral oppreſſions and injuries done unto them, contrary to the good Laws and cuſtoms of the Realm; whereupon King <hi>Edward,</hi> by his Royal Letters to the ſeveral She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs of <hi>England,</hi> commanded that in all Counties, Cities, and Market Towns, a Proclamation ſhould be made, that all who found themſelves agrieved ſhould repair to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> at the next Parliament, and there ſhew their grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, where as well the great as the leſs ſhould receive fit remedies and ſpeedy Juſtice, according as the King was obliged by the Bond of his Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:100111:80"/>Oath: And now that great day was come, that day of judging, even the Juſtices and the other Miniſters of the Kings Council, which by no Colluſion or Reward, no Argument or Art of Pleading they could elude or avoid: The Clergy therefore and the People being gathered together and ſeated in the great Palace of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury (a man of eminent Piety, and as it were a Pillar of the holy Church &amp; the Kingdom)</hi> riſing from his Seat, and fetching a profound ſigh, ſpoke in this manner: Let this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly know that we are called together concerning the great and weighty Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the Kingdom (too much alas of late diſturbed, and ſtill out of Order) unanimouſly, faithfully and effectually with our Lord the King to treat and ordain: Ye have all heard the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous complaints of the moſt intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble injuries and oppreſſions of the dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſolations committed both on Church and State, by this corrupt Council of
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:100111:81"/>our Lord the King, contrary to our great Charters, ſo many and ſo often, purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and redeemed, granted and confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us by the ſeveral Oaths of our Lord the King that now is, and of our Lords King <hi>Henry</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roborated by the dreadful thundrings of the ſentence of Ecommunication againſt the Invaders of our common Liberties of <hi>England</hi> in our ſaid Charters contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and when we had conceived firm and undoubted hopes, that theſe our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties would have been faithfully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by all men, the King circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented and ſeduced by the councils of evil Miniſters hath not been afraid to violate it by infringing them, falſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving that he could for Rewards be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved from that offence, which would be the manifeſt deſtruction of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>There is another thing alſo that grieves our Spirits that the Juſtices ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly and maliciouſly, by diverſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of covetouſneſs and intollerable Pride, have the King againſt his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Subjects ſundry ways incited and
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:100111:82"/>provok'd, counſelling him contrary to the good and wholſome Advice of all the Liegemen of <hi>England,</hi> and have not bluſh'd nor been afraid, impudently to aſſert and <hi>prefer their own fooliſh Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, as if they were more fit to conſult and preſerve the Commonweal, than all the Eſtates of the Kingdom toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aſſembled,</hi> ſo that it may be truly ſaid of them, they are the men that troubled the Land, and diſturb'd the Nation under a falſe colour of gravity, have the whole People grievouſly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, and under pretence of expounding the antient Laws, have introduced new (I will not ſay Laws, but) evil Cuſtoms, ſo that through the Ignorance of ſome, &amp; partiality of others, who for reward or fear of great Men have been engaged, there was no certainty of Law, and they ſcorned to adminiſter juſtice to the people, their deeds are deeds of wickedneſs, &amp; the work of Iniquity is in their hand, their feet make haſt to evil, &amp; the way of truth have they not known; what ſhall I ſay? there is no Judgment in their paths.<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:100111:83"/>build their Houſes in injuſtice, and their Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles in Unrighteouſneſs: Wee be to them that covet large poſſeſſions, that break open Houſes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Man and his Inheritance; Woe be to ſuch Judges who are like Wolves in the Evening, and leave not a bone till the morning. The Righteous Judge will bring ſuch Counſellors to a fooliſh end, and ſuch Judges to confuſion: ye ſhall all preſently with a loud cry, receive the juſt ſentence of the Land.</p>
            <p>At the hearing of theſe things all Ears tingled, and the whole Community lifted up their Voice, and mourned, ſaying, Alas, alas for us! what is become of that <hi>Engliſh Liberty</hi> which we have ſo often purchaſed, which by ſo many Conceſſions ſo many Statutes, ſo many Oaths hath been confirmed to us.</p>
            <p>Hereupon ſeveral of the Criminals withdrew into ſecret places, being concealed by their friends; ſome of them were brought forth into the midſt of the People, and deſervedly turned out of their Offices; one was baniſhed the Land, and others were grievouſly Fined, or Condemned to perpetual Impriſonment.
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:100111:84"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="168" facs="tcp:100111:85"/>
            <p> This is confirmed by <hi>Spelman An. 1290.</hi> All the Juſtices of <hi>England,</hi> ſaith he, were <hi>An. 18. Ed. 1.</hi> apprehended for Corruption, except <hi>John Mettingham,</hi> and <hi>Elias Bleckingham,</hi> whom I name for their honour, and by Judgment of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament condemned, ſome to Impriſonment, others Baniſhment, or Confiſcation of their Eſtates, and none eſcaped without grievous Fines, and the loſs of their Offices.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100111:85"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
